<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd"><eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511"><eadid countrycode="US" url="http://hdl.handle.net/10427/37895">UA193</eadid><filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper>University Microfilm Collection<num>UA193</num></titleproper></titlestmt><publicationstmt><publisher>Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University</publisher><p id="logostmt"><extref xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:href="https://dca.tufts.edu/themes/custom/dca_foundation/images/logos/full_with_icon.svg" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple"/></p><address><addressline>35 Professors Row</addressline><addressline>Tisch Library Building</addressline><addressline>Tufts University</addressline><addressline>Medford, Massachusetts 02155</addressline><addressline>archives@tufts.edu</addressline><addressline>URL: <extptr xlink:href="https://dca.tufts.edu/" xlink:show="new" xlink:title="https://dca.tufts.edu/" xlink:type="simple"/></addressline></address></publicationstmt></filedesc><profiledesc><creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on <date>2021-04-10 18:02:28 -0400</date>.</creation></profiledesc></eadheader><archdesc level="collection">
  <did>
    <repository>
      <corpname>Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University</corpname>
    </repository>
    <unittitle>University Microfilm Collection</unittitle>
    <origination label="Creator">
      <corpname source="local">Tufts University</corpname>
    </origination>
    <origination label="Creator">
      <corpname source="local">Tufts College</corpname>
    </origination>
    <unitid>UA193</unitid>
    <physdesc altrender="whole">
      <extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">0.5 Linear Feet</extent>
      <extent altrender="carrier">1 box</extent>
    </physdesc>
    <unitdate normal="1878/1985" type="inclusive">1878 -- 1985</unitdate>
    <langmaterial id="aspace_23e665cccf95213d18d9a24b39e7c97e">English</langmaterial>
  </did>
  <arrangement id="aspace_fbfeebbee23bca705223df5b4a28723f">
    <head>Arrangement</head>
<p>This collection is organized into one series: University microfilm.</p>  </arrangement>
  <custodhist id="aspace_f531e4aedf3cdd6a42c84e534c9e416d">
    <head>Custodial History</head>
<p>Microfilm reels are arranged according to their reel number.</p>  </custodhist>
  <scopecontent id="aspace_fbeee626ad3be5f4e7e59beedd9264af">
    <head>Scope and Contents</head>
<p>This is an artificial collection comprised of microfilm  created by the Tufts University library system during the 1960s and 1970s.  When possible, microfilm reels are housed with their related collection.  However, in a few cases, multiple collections are represented on individual reels.  Those cases are housed in the University Microfilm Collection.  Collections included on these reels include the Office of the President, the Office of the Provost, the Board of Trustees, the School of Medicine, the School of Dental Medicine, the School of Occupational Therapy, and New England Medical Center.  Also included are unspecified Tufts Magazines from October 1982.</p>  </scopecontent>
  <relatedmaterial id="aspace_6dc11e51d7d0bfe2974b3e59e4a765cb">
    <head>Related Materials</head>
<p>UA001, Office of the President records, DCA</p><p>UA002, Office of the Provost and Senior Vice President records, DCA</p><p>UA003, Office of the Board of Trustees records, DCA</p><p>UA010, School of Medicine records, DCA</p><p>UA020, School of Dental Medicine records, DCA</p><p>UA032, Boston School of Occupational Therapy (BSOT) records, DCA</p><p>UA144, Tufts Medical Center records, DCA</p>  </relatedmaterial>
  <bioghist id="aspace_26333a6a5c744c3cd493366a39430cd0">
    <head>Biographical / Historical</head>
<p>Tufts College was founded in 1852 by a group of Universalists who had for years worked to open a non-sectarian institution of higher learning.</p><p>By 1830, Universalist efforts to build an institution of higher learning were increasing in both frequency and strength. Many Universalist ministers and laymen alike felt that their community needed a school that intertwined theological and liberal arts courses. Their opponents, however, feared the creation of a theological institution, as they felt it would create clerical domination, and prevent uneducated but devoted Universalists from becoming clergymen.</p><p>In 1835, at the annual General Convention, Thomas Jefferson Sawyer, a prominent Universalist, put forth a recommendation calling for the question of establishing a Theological Seminary to be put to the denomination at large. The resolution was adopted, and for the next four years, Sawyer's colleague, Reverend Thomas Whittemore, worked tirelessly to drum up support, both through columns in the Universalist paper, "The Trumpet," and through speeches.</p><p>By this time it had become clear that a Universalist theological college was a necessary step for the advancement of the religion. Hosea Ballou 2nd, a prolific writer and well-known minister, served as a teacher for many young Universalists interested in joining the clergy. The demand for his teaching had become so great that he had begun to teach classes instead of individual students. This high demand illustrated the need for an official school, planned for either upstate New York or the Boston, Massachusetts, area.</p><p>At the Massachusetts State Convention in 1840, attendees authorized the creation of a board of trustees to raise funds, find a site, and erect the buildings for a Universalist college. The committee included both Hosea Ballou and his son, Hosea Ballou 2nd. After the creation of the board, serious fundraising began, with a goal of $50,000 set for the campaign. Due to a lack of popular support and internal tension on the board, the first effort eventually failed.</p><p>In 1847, another fundraising drive began, this time with a goal of $100,000. Otis Skinner, another prominent Universalist, was selected to head the fundraising team. By 1851, Skinner and his team had reached the goal. By this time, the trustees had also selected the site of the future college. Earlier in the decade, Charles Tufts had donated $20,000 worth of Medford land to the trustees with the stipulation that the college be built on the site. This caused a rift among the trustees. Some felt that the college belonged in New York, others voted for Springfield, and even Hosea Ballou 2nd felt that the Tufts location was too close to Harvard and Boston. The question was put to a vote, and eventually the Medford site prevailed.</p><p>On April 22, 1852, Massachusetts granted a charter to the Trustees of Tufts College for the establishment of an institution of higher learning. The now official Trustees attempted to elect Thomas Jefferson Sawyer as the first president of Tufts, but his salary demands were too high. By 1853, Hosea Ballou 2nd had been selected as the institution's first president. By the fall of 1854, Tufts College, though not yet formally opened, had begun operation. On August 22, 1855, the college held a formal opening, and the first formal term saw over thirty students enrolled.</p><p>Tufts College continued as a liberal arts institution until the fall of 1869, when the Divinity School officially opened. In his will, benefactor Sylvanius Packard had earmarked $300,000 for Tufts, but stipulated that part of the trust must go to the establishment of a Professorship of Christian Theology. Hoping to remain a non-sectarian school, Tufts instead opted to found a separate and quasi-independent Divinity School. In 1906, the Divinity School was renamed the Crane Theological School, and continued operation until 1968.</p><p>The next major event in early Tufts history was the decision to become a co-educational institution. After ten years of debate, the Trustees finally decided to bring women to Tufts College in 1892. Although men and women originally took classes together, Tufts provided separate housing and dining facilities. By the first decade of the twentieth century, however, many administrators were becoming more and more opposed to co-education. Tufts had seen a drop in male enrollment, and many worried that it was because of the presence of women in classes. Women had also begun to dominate academically. In 1906, for example, all five seniors elected to Phi Beta Kappa were female. The co-education question was solved in 1910 using funds from an 1895 grant. Cornelia Marie Jackson had left half of her estate to Tufts to improve facilities for women, including a stipulation that a building be constructed and named The Cornelia M. Jackson College for Women. In 1910, the Trustees decided to use Jackson's funds to create a coordinate college. Jackson was to be separate from Tufts, with female only classes, dormitories, and dining halls. The Trustees felt it was the best way to improve male enrollment without alienating women. Male and female students remained segregated until 1913, when classes were again made co-educational.</p><p>Soon after Tufts became co-educational, an opportunity for a new branch of the college appeared in Boston. In 1893, seven faculty members from the College of Physicians and Surgeons, dissatisfied with their employer, left the school and with the backing of Tufts College formed the Tufts School of Medicine. The downtown Boston school soon spawned another branch. In 1899, Tufts acquired the Boston Dental College, and the renamed Tufts School of Dental Medicine began operation in close coordination with the Tufts School of Medicine.</p><p>
Tufts continued its expansion into the twentieth century. In 1933, with a bequest from trustee Austin B. Fletcher, Tufts opened the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. The school, opened with the collaboration of Harvard University, became the first graduate school of international affairs in the United States. It also brought tremendous prestige to Tufts, which was quickly gaining a reputation as an excellent school.</p><p>Expansion continued into the 1940's, when Tufts allied with the Bouve-Boston School of Physical Therapy and Physical Education in 1942. In 1945, Tufts formed alliances with both the School of the Museum of Fine Arts and the Boston School of Occupational Therapy. In 1951, Tufts began operating the Boston Nursery Training School as a separate entity under the College of Special Studies. In 1955, the school was renamed the Eliot Pearson Children's School.</p><p>1955 brought another important change for Tufts. A petition from the Trustees dated January 20, 1955, and approved on January 28, officially changed the name of the school to Tufts University. The name change, one of President Nils Y. Wessell's original goals, was cited as both an official recognition of an already established event, and also as a recognition of a desirable direction for Tufts to move in.</p>  </bioghist>
  <processinfo id="aspace_fdf73023f609dbb3dfe0985b8c6dc77a">
    <head>Processing status</head>
<p>This collection is processed.</p>  </processinfo>
  <accessrestrict id="aspace_40e5493cd979c7ae3b497b0f78763ae8">
    <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
<p>Open for research.</p>  </accessrestrict>
  <userestrict id="aspace_910296946ca59862396b95a838487c2e">
    <head>Conditions Governing Use</head>
<p>Some material in this collection may be protected by copyright and other rights. Please see "Reproductions and Use" on the Digital Collections and Archives website for more information about reproductions and permission to publish. Copyright to all materials created by Tufts University employees in the course of their work is held by the Trustees of Tufts University.</p>  </userestrict>
  <controlaccess>
    <subject source="local">Administration and Governance -- Governance</subject>
    <subject source="local">Curriculum and Instruction -- Faculty</subject>
  </controlaccess>
  <dsc><c id="aspace_7f99f1005350af1e894760fec5e26522" level="series"><did><unittitle>University Microfilm Collection</unittitle><unitid>UA193.001</unitid><physdesc altrender="whole"><extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">0.5 Linear Feet</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1878/1985" type="inclusive">1878 -- 1985</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><arrangement id="aspace_0c73b3805b3583461b603b9c41187b15"><head>Arrangement</head><p>The collection is arranged according to reel number.</p></arrangement><accessrestrict id="aspace_25c3ef9f14bb31a62cf000c773008762"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><c id="aspace_127079d97ee838cfdece190a6a0ad39b" level="item"><did><unittitle>Reel No. 63-27: Boston Dental College 1878-1902, Dental Faculty 1914-30, Pre-Med Faculty 1916-29; Faculty Papers 1926-46</unittitle><unitid>UA193.001.001.00001</unitid><unitdate normal="1878/1946" type="inclusive">1878 -- 1946</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container altrender="Letter size document box" id="aspace_855f17647387f4a45b843eb6ed19c983" label="audio_or_moving_images [39090014014100]" type="box">1</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_e47623c983c86342145530574839e223"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_e96c7395dd207361848514359279ae91"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p></p>
<p>1 1/2 inch film; 63-27 Boston Dental College Trustees Minutes Jan 2, 1878-Sept. 24, 1902; School of Dental Medicine Faculty Minutes October 16, 1914-March 12, 1930; Tufts College Pre-Dental Faculty Minutes 1916-1929; Tufts College Pre-Medical Faculty Minutes 1916-1929; Tufts College Faculty Office Papers 1925-1946</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><genreform source="local">microfilms</genreform><corpname source="local">School of Dental Medicine</corpname><corpname source="local">School of Medicine</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_549cfd8260c87299aae9a456901d29b9" level="item"><did><unittitle>Reel No. 63-28: Dental Medicine 1914-59, School of Medicine Faculty 1893-1934</unittitle><unitid>UA193.001.001.00002</unitid><unitdate normal="1893/1959" type="inclusive">1893 -- 1959</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container altrender="Letter size document box" id="aspace_1b1de4636b5265039ad98b2b806a0ca8" label="audio_or_moving_images [39090014014100]" type="box">1</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_f1df5a52c25e3045b053e2743a7deda1"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_4a786dd2434644a35a8191a405750880"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>1 1/2 inch film; 63-28 School of Dental Medicine Administrative Committee Minutes Sept 3, 1914-June 2, 1959, School of Dental Med. Faculty Minutes April 15, 1930-Feb. 12, 1958, School of Medicine Faculty Minutes Aug 19, 1893-April 10, 1934</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><genreform source="local">microfilms</genreform><corpname source="local">School of Dental Medicine</corpname><corpname source="local">School of Medicine</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_3c2b83908f817f3ae906449c8f71d4cd" level="item"><did><unittitle>Reel No. 85: Various Minutes (Faculty Minutes 1961-63, Occupational Therapy 1960-76, Dental Medicine 1959-76, Medicine 1963-76 N.E. Medical Center 1964-76)</unittitle><unitid>UA193.001.001.00003</unitid><unitdate normal="1959/1976" type="inclusive">1959 -- 1976</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container altrender="Letter size document box" id="aspace_0ba5678be5eae5370eb3e376e6bbd548" label="audio_or_moving_images [39090014014100]" type="box">1</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_75eaad64ddf56d1e26f1fb251122d1f4"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_95d0c409a1e87bdb02ca1a40c9f85b63"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>1/2 inch film; Various Minutes; START: Faculty Min Medford Campus 1961-1963, Boston School Occupational Therapy 1960-1976, School of Dental Medicine 1959-1976, School of Medicine 1963-1976 END: New England Medical Center Inc. 1964-1976 Admin Board Min.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><genreform source="local">microfilms</genreform><corpname source="local">Office of the Provost</corpname><corpname source="local">School of Dental Medicine</corpname><corpname source="local">School of Medicine</corpname><corpname source="local">New England Medical Center</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_e4962768a18513775ca9ec8752c32bd2" level="item"><did><unittitle>Reel No. 86: Various Minutes (N.E. Medical Center, President's Annual Report)</unittitle><unitid>UA193.001.001.00004</unitid><unitdate normal="1964/1976" type="inclusive">1964 -- 1976</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container altrender="Letter size document box" id="aspace_4e3b011f333c769642b24bb1c41d5d32" label="audio_or_moving_images [39090014014100]" type="box">1</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_e13bfd78cc317bf83f7c5f4d7b80146b"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_98a6e0a416dbe4533761b2c5fc261b45"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>1/2 inch film; Various Minutes; START: New England Medical Center Inc. Admin Committee 1966-1976 END: Presidents Annual Reports to the Trustees October 1964 to October 1971</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><genreform source="local">microfilms</genreform><corpname source="local">New England Medical Center</corpname><corpname source="local">Office of the President</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_afa997eb545a70c026c41ead20c13cfe" level="item"><did><unittitle>Reel No. 104-A: Minutes (Trustees Educational Policy, President's Annual Report)</unittitle><unitid>UA193.001.001.00005</unitid><unitdate normal="1962/1978" type="inclusive">1962 -- 1978</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container altrender="Letter size document box" id="aspace_8ed215d1f3613a79fc0c609006143ce4" label="audio_or_moving_images [39090014014100]" type="box">1</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_ced1211260bc712af719f8977bc6a882"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_7816ae850e5e1cb1fb3ec20376afdae4"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>1/2 inch film; Minutes; START: Trustees Educational Policy Dec. 6, 1962 May 25, 1967 END: President's Annual Report to the Trustees Nov. 1977 and October 78</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><genreform source="local">microfilms</genreform><corpname source="local">Board of Trustees</corpname><corpname source="local">Office of the President</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_d8e97f760bca145004c04f408395cd9a" level="item"><did><unittitle>Reel No. 110a: Minutes (Faculty Records, Trustees Minutes, President's Annual Report)</unittitle><unitid>UA193.001.001.00006</unitid><unitdate normal="1974/1980" type="inclusive">1974 -- 1980</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container altrender="Letter size document box" id="aspace_6901749bc2e1e631666bc0b587967982" label="audio_or_moving_images [39090014014100]" type="box">1</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_3229456496c2338af8d46f3da9b158c0"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_267c451a16abbe5d62ba404ff4436163"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>1/2 inch film; Minutes; START: Faculty Records 1979-1980 Vols. 84 &amp; 85, Trustees Minutes 1974-1979, Executive Committee, Finance Committee, Educational Policy Committee, Resources Development Committee, Building &amp; Grounds Committee END: President's Annual Report to Trustees Nov. 3, 1979 Oct. 31, 1980</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><genreform source="local">microfilms</genreform></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_db22890f9f33734aaa620b66c6f6618a" level="item"><did><unittitle>Reel No. 124: President's Report (Annual Report of the President, Tufts Magazine)</unittitle><unitid>UA193.001.001.00007</unitid><unitdate normal="1981/1982" type="inclusive">1981 -- 1982</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container altrender="Letter size document box" id="aspace_c38e490a2237cec963c9a99a740d2290" label="audio_or_moving_images [39090014014100]" type="box">1</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_988525a72951e05696c79c526c4f5016"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_aea2906afd255c0e6db819e3888fbeb2"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>1/2 inch film; START: Annual report of Presidents October 23, 1981 Series 2.11 END: Tufts Magazines October 1982 Series 6.17</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><genreform source="local">microfilms</genreform><corpname source="local">Office of the President</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_4e9d63d8367591eee009b9b2f05f9387" level="item"><did><unittitle>Reel No. 135: Presidents Report (Trustees Full Board Minutes, Presidents Report)</unittitle><unitid>UA193.001.001.00008</unitid><unitdate normal="1983/1985" type="inclusive">1983 -- 1985</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container altrender="Letter size document box" id="aspace_8c1fac4bfea547e7d22e8360d881b4c2" label="audio_or_moving_images [39090014014100]" type="box">1</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_a056d9c583095957950439ab74a0d7de"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_ccdaf3615db75ff764338c2f276472ab"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>1/2 inch film; Tufts University Trustee Full Board Minutes START: 11-4-83 - 2-23-85  END: Presidents RPT 1983</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><genreform source="local">microfilms</genreform></controlaccess></c></c></dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
