<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd"><eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511"><eadid countrycode="US" url="http://hdl.handle.net/10427/48193">MS080</eadid><filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper>Tufts Oral History Project Records<num>MS080</num></titleproper></titlestmt><publicationstmt><publisher>Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University</publisher><p id="logostmt"><extref xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:href="https://dca.tufts.edu/themes/custom/dca_foundation/images/logos/full_with_icon.svg" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple"/></p><address><addressline>35 Professors Row</addressline><addressline>Tisch Library Building</addressline><addressline>Tufts University</addressline><addressline>Medford, Massachusetts 02155</addressline><addressline>archives@tufts.edu</addressline><addressline>URL: <extptr xlink:href="https://dca.tufts.edu/" xlink:show="new" xlink:title="https://dca.tufts.edu/" xlink:type="simple"/></addressline></address></publicationstmt></filedesc><profiledesc><creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on <date>2021-04-10 19:11:41 -0400</date>.</creation></profiledesc></eadheader><archdesc level="collection">
  <did>
    <repository>
      <corpname>Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University</corpname>
    </repository>
    <unittitle>Tufts Oral History Project Records</unittitle>
    <origination label="Creator">
      <corpname source="local">Tufts College</corpname>
    </origination>
    <unitid>MS080</unitid>
    <physdesc altrender="whole">
      <extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">1.2 Linear Feet</extent>
    </physdesc>
    <unitdate normal="2001/2001" type="inclusive">2001</unitdate>
    <langmaterial id="aspace_f7708894ff0265e28667556fcac05aa3">English</langmaterial>
  </did>
  <custodhist id="aspace_71c6c55d08228c3088c491d1386dbcd8">
    <head>Custodial History</head>
<p>Creator: Laura Ferguson</p>  </custodhist>
  <scopecontent id="aspace_bad421e757d90c9f1ee7d6feabaf4635">
    <head>Scope and Contents</head>
<p>This collection contains audiotapes, cds with digital audio, transcripts, release forms, notes, and news clippings of interviews with Tufts alumni for the Tufts Oral History Project. The Tufts Oral History Project was a project created for the 150th celebration of the university in 2002. The bulk of the material dates from 2001 and consists of the audio files and transcripts of the interviews. The project was led by Laura Ferguson who was the associate director of communications and marketing for alumni relations at that time. Fourteen oral histories were collected from men and women of Tufts from a range of classes from 1925 to 1949. The interviews cover a range of topics including perceptions of Tufts, what led students to apply, social customs at Tufts, interactions between Jackson College women and Tufts men, memories of teachers and deans, and life and work after leaving Tufts. These oral histories provide insight to university and campus life during the Depression and World War II. </p>  </scopecontent>
  <bioghist id="aspace_f8f9d75f375f4633bcd7f7963a4926b0">
    <head>Biographical / Historical</head>
<p>Tufts College was founded in 1852 by a group of Universalists who had for years worked to open a non-sectarian institution of higher learning.</p><p>By 1830, Universalist efforts to build an institution of higher learning were increasing in both frequency and strength. Many Universalist ministers and laymen alike felt that their community needed a school that intertwined theological and liberal arts courses. Their opponents, however, feared the creation of a theological institution, as they felt it would create clerical domination, and prevent uneducated but devoted Universalists from becoming clergymen.</p><p>In 1835, at the annual General Convention, Thomas Jefferson Sawyer, a prominent Universalist, put forth a recommendation calling for the question of establishing a Theological Seminary to be put to the denomination at large. The resolution was adopted, and for the next four years, Sawyer's colleague, Reverend Thomas Whittemore, worked tirelessly to drum up support, both through columns in the Universalist paper, "The Trumpet," and through speeches.</p><p>By this time it had become clear that a Universalist theological college was a necessary step for the advancement of the religion. Hosea Ballou 2nd, a prolific writer and well-known minister, served as a teacher for many young Universalists interested in joining the clergy. The demand for his teaching had become so great that he had begun to teach classes instead of individual students. This high demand illustrated the need for an official school, planned for either upstate New York or the Boston, Massachusetts, area.</p><p>At the Massachusetts State Convention in 1840, attendees authorized the creation of a board of trustees to raise funds, find a site, and erect the buildings for a Universalist college. The committee included both Hosea Ballou and his son, Hosea Ballou 2nd. After the creation of the board, serious fundraising began, with a goal of $50,000 set for the campaign. Due to a lack of popular support and internal tension on the board, the first effort eventually failed.</p><p>In 1847, another fundraising drive began, this time with a goal of $100,000. Otis Skinner, another prominent Universalist, was selected to head the fundraising team. By 1851, Skinner and his team had reached the goal. By this time, the trustees had also selected the site of the future college. Earlier in the decade, Charles Tufts had donated $20,000 worth of Medford land to the trustees with the stipulation that the college be built on the site. This caused a rift among the trustees. Some felt that the college belonged in New York, others voted for Springfield, and even Hosea Ballou 2nd felt that the Tufts location was too close to Harvard and Boston. The question was put to a vote, and eventually the Medford site prevailed.</p><p>On April 22, 1852, Massachusetts granted a charter to the Trustees of Tufts College for the establishment of an institution of higher learning. The now official Trustees attempted to elect Thomas Jefferson Sawyer as the first president of Tufts, but his salary demands were too high. By 1853, Hosea Ballou 2nd had been selected as the institution's first president. By the fall of 1854, Tufts College, though not yet formally opened, had begun operation. On August 22, 1855, the college held a formal opening, and the first formal term saw over thirty students enrolled.</p><p>Tufts College continued as a liberal arts institution until the fall of 1869, when the Divinity School officially opened. In his will, benefactor Sylvanius Packard had earmarked $300,000 for Tufts, but stipulated that part of the trust must go to the establishment of a Professorship of Christian Theology. Hoping to remain a non-sectarian school, Tufts instead opted to found a separate and quasi-independent Divinity School. In 1906, the Divinity School was renamed the Crane Theological School, and continued operation until 1968.</p><p>The next major event in early Tufts history was the decision to become a co-educational institution. After ten years of debate, the Trustees finally decided to bring women to Tufts College in 1892. Although men and women originally took classes together, Tufts provided separate housing and dining facilities. By the first decade of the twentieth century, however, many administrators were becoming more and more opposed to co-education. Tufts had seen a drop in male enrollment, and many worried that it was because of the presence of women in classes. Women had also begun to dominate academically. In 1906, for example, all five seniors elected to Phi Beta Kappa were female. The co-education question was solved in 1910 using funds from an 1895 grant. Cornelia Marie Jackson had left half of her estate to Tufts to improve facilities for women, including a stipulation that a building be constructed and named The Cornelia M. Jackson College for Women. In 1910, the Trustees decided to use Jackson's funds to create a coordinate college. Jackson was to be separate from Tufts, with female only classes, dormitories, and dining halls. The Trustees felt it was the best way to improve male enrollment without alienating women. Male and female students remained segregated until 1913, when classes were again made co-educational.</p><p>Soon after Tufts became co-educational, an opportunity for a new branch of the college appeared in Boston. In 1893, seven faculty members from the College of Physicians and Surgeons, dissatisfied with their employer, left the school and with the backing of Tufts College formed the Tufts School of Medicine. The downtown Boston school soon spawned another branch. In 1899, Tufts acquired the Boston Dental College, and the renamed Tufts School of Dental Medicine began operation in close coordination with the Tufts School of Medicine.</p><p>
Tufts continued its expansion into the twentieth century. In 1933, with a bequest from trustee Austin B. Fletcher, Tufts opened the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. The school, opened with the collaboration of Harvard University, became the first graduate school of international affairs in the United States. It also brought tremendous prestige to Tufts, which was quickly gaining a reputation as an excellent school.</p><p>Expansion continued into the 1940's, when Tufts allied with the Bouve-Boston School of Physical Therapy and Physical Education in 1942. In 1945, Tufts formed alliances with both the School of the Museum of Fine Arts and the Boston School of Occupational Therapy. In 1951, Tufts began operating the Boston Nursery Training School as a separate entity under the College of Special Studies. In 1955, the school was renamed the Eliot Pearson Children's School.</p><p>1955 brought another important change for Tufts. A petition from the Trustees dated January 20, 1955, and approved on January 28, officially changed the name of the school to Tufts University. The name change, one of President Nils Y. Wessell's original goals, was cited as both an official recognition of an already established event, and also as a recognition of a desirable direction for Tufts to move in.</p>  </bioghist>
  <processinfo id="aspace_5465484e8fdb38b465f10f26680c3e6c">
    <head>Processing status</head>
<p>This collection is minimally processed.</p>  </processinfo>
  <accessrestrict id="aspace_463769897df15f44718724582f47b8b5">
    <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
<p>Access to this collection is restricted. The collection is closed for 75 years due to privacy concerns.</p>  </accessrestrict>
  <userestrict id="aspace_2a3718efaf736d30144916f515118174">
    <head>Conditions Governing Use</head>
<p>Some material in this collection may be protected by copyright and other rights. Please see "Reproductions and Use" on the Digital Collections and Archives website for more information about reproductions and permission to publish. No documentation is available regarding the intellectual property rights in this collection.</p>  </userestrict>
  <controlaccess>
    <title source="local">Tufts University</title>
    <subject source="local">College Students -- United States -- Social Life And Customs</subject>
    <title source="local">Oral histories</title>
    <subject source="local">University history</subject>
  </controlaccess>
  <dsc><c id="aspace_daf582eb31fc26ecdede414f57bc4bc4" level="series"><did><unittitle>Additional accessions</unittitle><unitid>MS080.001</unitid><physdesc altrender="whole"><extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">1 Volumes</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="2001/2001" type="inclusive">2001</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_7c0cbc9e322c85ea915ad79b23de5b9e"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><c id="aspace_40d5a6a1fee1f0ddd71104f04cfd123a" level="file"><did><unittitle>Tufts Oral History Project</unittitle><unitid>MS080.001.GB</unitid><unitdate normal="2001/2001">2001</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container id="aspace_115e8b35c692162c85b00295c547de4c" label="Mixed Materials [39090017911237]" type="box">1</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_d0063034b95ee1577853305c8ea54091"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_a1c3fe4173f3693656d55e1ffe929386"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>Former barcode 39090011500630g.</p></scopecontent></c></c></dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
