<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd"><eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511"><eadid countrycode="US" url="http://hdl.handle.net/10427/48256">UA071</eadid><filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper>Department of Education Records<num>UA071</num></titleproper></titlestmt><publicationstmt><publisher>Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University</publisher><p id="logostmt"><extref xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:href="https://dca.tufts.edu/themes/custom/dca_foundation/images/logos/full_with_icon.svg" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple"/></p><address><addressline>35 Professors Row</addressline><addressline>Tisch Library Building</addressline><addressline>Tufts University</addressline><addressline>Medford, Massachusetts 02155</addressline><addressline>archives@tufts.edu</addressline><addressline>URL: <extptr xlink:href="https://dca.tufts.edu/" xlink:show="new" xlink:title="https://dca.tufts.edu/" xlink:type="simple"/></addressline></address></publicationstmt></filedesc><profiledesc><creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on <date>2021-04-05 03:17:32 -0400</date>.</creation></profiledesc></eadheader><archdesc level="collection">
  <did>
    <repository>
      <corpname>Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University</corpname>
    </repository>
    <unittitle>Department of Education Records</unittitle>
    <origination label="Creator">
      <corpname source="local">Department of Education</corpname>
    </origination>
    <unitid>UA071</unitid>
    <physdesc altrender="part">
      <extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">1.2 Linear Feet</extent>
      <extent altrender="carrier">1 box</extent>
    </physdesc>
    <physdesc altrender="part">
      <extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">31 Digital Object(s)</extent>
    </physdesc>
    <unitdate normal="1954/2014" type="inclusive">1954 -- 2014</unitdate>
    <langmaterial>
      <language langcode="eng">English</language>
.    </langmaterial>
  </did>
  <accessrestrict id="aspace_1670e6d49338a54ec76e56d6d735ea8f">
    <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
<p>This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.</p>  </accessrestrict>
  <arrangement id="aspace_2c502930145e9382d58cabde18770228">
    <head>Arrangement</head>
<p>This collection is organized in three series: Qualifying papers; Unprocessed accessions; and 2017 accessions.</p>  </arrangement>
  <bioghist id="aspace_426222c723733c1ad55987dab701a86e">
    <head>Biographical / Historical</head>
<p>In the first years of the twentieth century, half-year courses in Pedagogy-later changed to Education-were taught by Professor Herbert E. Cushman of the Department of Philosophy, assisted by teachers from local secondary schools. The Chair of Psychology and Education was created for the academic year 1910-1911, and was filled by Colin A. Scott, formerly of the Boston Normal School and the author of Social Education. The catalog for that year states that "The work of the department is expected not only to prepare for teaching but to give a general idea of the facts of mental life, to study human and animal behavior in such a way as to be valuable to any student." Laboratory work would supplement reading, discussion and lectures. By the next year, however, Scott was gone, the heading was again simply Education, and psychology courses reverted back to the Department of Philosophy.</p><p>The next step forward for education studies came in the academic year of 1912-1913, when students were given the opportunity for observation and practice teaching in the schools of nearby Somerville. In the catalog for 1915-1916, the list of major departments included the combined entity Philosophy and Education. Students who desired to go into the teaching profession were advised to choose as their major the subject in which they intended to specialize. They should take the introductory Education classes, and pursue further Education courses for their graduate work.</p><p>As of 1924-1925, Education and Philosophy became separate departments. For the next few decades, the number of courses in the Department of Education steadily increased. To classes in the history and philosophy of education were added offerings in the social sciences, some of which concerned the measurement of learning outcomes. The Supervised Teaching component expanded to Arlington, Medford, Chelsea, Winchester and Melrose.</p><p>The 1939-1940 catalog stated that "the work of the Department includes a consideration of the pupil, the aims and desirable outcomes of the educational process itself, and the means and techniques for their most effectual achievement." The Department offered Master of Education and Master of Arts degrees. Students were alerted that different states have different certification requirements, so they should seek advice on how to tailor their course work accordingly. They were made aware of relevant courses taught in other departments, such as the teaching of English in the Department of English, history in the Department of History, modern languages in the Department of French, and physical education in the Department of Physical Education.</p><p>The academic year 1939-1940 saw the creation of the Division of University Extension (later called Division of Special Studies, then the College of Special Studies). The Division offered late afternoon, evening and weekend courses for the benefit of working schoolteachers. Classes were taught by members of the Tufts faculty. A Bachelor of Science in Education degree, offered to extension school students, was authorized in 1940.</p><p>Tufts entered into an affiliation with a number of teacher-training schools via the Division of University Extension. The student bodies of these affiliates were predominantly or solely made up of women.</p><p>The Bouv-Boston School of Physical Education, which became an affiliate 1942, offered courses of study in the teaching of physical education and in physical therapy. Bouv-Boston students could take liberal arts and basic science courses at Tufts. The school later moved to the Medford campus, but then ended its affiliation with Tufts in 1963 (whereupon it became associated with Northeastern University).</p><p>Tufts' affiliation with another institution proved more fruitful. The Nursery Training School of Boston, with which it affiliated in 1951, eventually grew into the Eliot-Pearson Department of Child Development. There had been an on-campus nursery school in 1940, which was suspended during the war years and did not reopen until 1949. It was dissolved upon Tufts' affiliation with the Nursery Training School of Boston, which had been founded in 1922 and was located on Marlborough St. in Boston. After its move to the Medford campus in 1954, the Nursery Training School (renamed in 1955 the Eliot-Pearson School for Nursery and Kindergarten Teaching) offered students of the Department of Education a chance to observe, as well as teach, young children. In 1964, the Eliot-Pearson School became the Eliot-Pearson Department of Child Study (later changed to Child Development).</p><p>The Department of Education grew during the postwar period, both in number of faculty members and courses offered to undergraduates and graduate students. Daniel Waite Marshall, then an assistant professor, became chairman in 1954, a position he would hold until 1971. An increasing area of focus was the training of prospective guidance counselors. In the academic year 1955-1956, a class in Citizenship Education was taught by members of the Tufts Civic Education Center. New course offerings in the 1960s included The Sociology of the School, Child Development (in association with the Judge Baker Guidance Center), and Education in Communist China (changed in the 1970s to Education in the People's Republic of China).</p><p>The department endeavored to welcome undergraduates who wanted to pursue a teaching career, graduate students working towards teacher certification, and working teachers who sought to further their education. To serve the latter population, an increasing number of courses were scheduled in the late afternoon, evenings, weekends, and summers. During the 1960s, the department started a Placement Office, through which a prospective teacher could learn about job opportunities in consultation with members of the nationwide network of Tufts alumni.</p><p>Degree requirements were further refined during this time. Undergraduates could follow a five-year program leading to a Master's degree. They were urged to decide early on whether to prepare for a career teaching in secondary or elementary school, since the respective accreditation requirements were different. The department had a recommended course selection list for each of those options. Student-teaching in local schools was emphasized as a crucial component of Tufts' teacher training. The graduate program offered Master of Arts and Master of Education degrees. The department identified several tracks which students could follow towards their degree. These included Preparation for Guidance, Teaching of Physically Handicapped Children (in cooperation with the Massachusetts Hospital School), Teaching the Emotionally Disturbed, Child Care Counselors, Health Professions, and, for a short time, Reading Specialist.</p><p>While a core group of courses persisted, there was some fluidity in offerings during the later decades of the century. Upon the establishment of the Eliot-Pearson Department of Child Study, some courses focusing on younger children migrated from the Department of Education to the newer department. Similarly, a cluster of courses centering on nutrition-offered in cooperation with the Department of Preventive Medicine together with the Frances Stern Food Clinic of the Boston Dispensary-moved out of the Department of Education during the 1980s and into the newly created Department of Nutrition. The department participated in the interdisciplinary Internship in Urban Social and Environmental Policy program in the late 1970s. Additions to the course offerings, such as Multicultural Concerns in Counseling and Psychotherapy, Learning Disabilities in the Classroom, and Teaching Through Drama and Improvisation continued to reflect contemporary issues and techniques.</p><p>In 1973, the department joined with the Department of Child Study to participate in a study-abroad program called Tufts in Education in England. Juniors and seniors were given the opportunity to attend the Alsager College of Teacher Education in Cheshire. The first enrollees took classes at Alsager in the spring semester of 1974. The program ended in 1978.</p><p>The academic year of 1991-1992 saw the launch of the H. Dudley Wright Program in Innovative Science Education, which offered fellowships for talented school science and mathematics teachers. According to the Wright Center's website in 2011, the institution is "dedicated to the creation and sharing of novel instructional techniques and interdisciplinary resources for pre-college teachers." The Wright program has been located in the Center for Science and Mathematics Teaching since its inception.</p><p>The late 1980s into the early 1990s was a period of flux as far as degree offerings were concerned. During this period, the Master of Education was discontinued. Thenceforth, candidates could pursue an M.A. or M.A.T. (Master of Arts in Teaching). In 1989, the undergraduate major in Education was discontinued (a minor in Education is still offered). Undergrads could choose a five-year B.A./M.A.T program. Starting in 1992, a C.A.G.S. (Certificate of Graduate Study) could be pursued in a specialized area, such as School Psychology. In the 1993-1994 academic year, the Department of Education and the School of the Museum of Fine Arts (which has been linked with Tufts for many years) collaborated to offer students who held a Bachelor of Fine Arts degree the chance to earn a certificate to teach art. This was followed by a Master of Arts program in Museum Education. The department similarly collaborated with the Department of Child Development to offer a certificate to teach elementary school children.</p><p>In the 2000s, a doctor of philosophy degree was offered in certain areas of specialization. There was a program to earn a Master of Science or a Ph.D. in Mathematics, Science, Technology and Education Engineering (MSTE Education), and one to earn an M.A. or Ph.D in German with Teaching Licensure (candidates were encouraged to take advantage of Tufts' study-abroad program in Tbingen, Germany). The decade also saw a number of M.A. degree programs created in association with specific institutions, such as the Shady Hill School in Cambridge, the Newton Teacher Training Institute in Newton, and the Advanced Math and Science Academy Charter School in Marlborough. In addition, an M.A. in Educational Studies was offered.</p><p>In the Department of Education's Faculty and Student Handbook of Programs and Degrees 2010-2011, ten different Master's degrees are listed, as well as the Ph.D. in MSTE Education (the Ph.D. in teaching German is no longer offered). The handbook lists as affiliated programs the Center for Science and Mathematics Teaching and the Center for Engineering Education Outreach.</p>  </bioghist>
  <processinfo id="aspace_0dad1b78da16249ff2b49c1a163d93fa">
    <head>Processing status</head>
<p>This collection is minimally processed.</p><p>Processing of 2017 accessions was completed by Leah Edelman in 2018. Materials were placed in archival boxes and received order was maintained. A file level inventory and series-level description were created and the finding aid was updated at the time of processing.  </p>  </processinfo>
  <scopecontent id="aspace_687595022cc542ebf38fcff4b20ee697">
    <head>Scope and Contents</head>
<p>This collection contains books, correspondence, qualifying papers of Department of Education students, reports, and a box of slides from an outdoor education camp. The construction of the Arthur M. Sackler Center for Health Communications is a significant topic in this collection.</p>  </scopecontent>
  <userestrict id="aspace_b80fd898a703bfa02748d39cd6f95b6a">
    <head>Conditions Governing Use</head>
<p>Some material in this collection may be protected by copyright and other rights. Please see "Reproductions and Use" on the Digital Collections and Archives website for more information about reproductions and permission to publish. Copyright to all materials created by Tufts University employees in the course of their work is held by the Trustees of Tufts University.</p>  </userestrict>
  <controlaccess>
    <subject source="local">Curriculum and Instruction -- Academic Departments and Programs</subject>
    <subject source="local">Curriculum and Instruction -- Student Work</subject>
    <subject source="local">Curriculum and Instruction -- Teaching Material</subject>
  </controlaccess>
  <dsc><c id="aspace_5733d2bfc53b14be15ae5a9376d25b0c" level="series"><did><unittitle>Qualifying papers</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001</unitid><physdesc altrender="whole"><extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">26 Digital Object(s)</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="2007/2014" type="inclusive">2007 -- 2014</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><scopecontent id="aspace_79ad37b858cf6831e27b77485d6ccf8e"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>This series contains selected papers submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for various degree programs in the Department of Education.</p></scopecontent><arrangement id="aspace_eff6bd2c6ea55a0186333bc650f52752"><head>Arrangement</head><p>This series is arranged alphabetically by author.</p></arrangement><accessrestrict id="aspace_d6e167680519580471467cf431286775"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><c id="aspace_74d6ecd493473d29f32e437297ce7308" level="item"><did><unittitle>From Functions as Process to Functions as Object: A Review of Reification and Encapsulation</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00001</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Burnett-Bradshaw, Camille S.</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2007-02-01/2007-02-01">2007-02-01</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_6334e107e56831fe459e99460326ce42"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_07bb6b8248f972a09a09d03f0e0be01e"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Mathematics Education. Abstract: This qualifying paper explores the processes of reification (Sfard, 1987, 1989, 1991, 1992) and encapsulation (Dubinsky, 1991a, 1991b; Dubinsky &amp; Harel, 1992a), as they apply to the concept of mathematical functions, and attempts to determine how both processes contribute to explaining the formation of the concept of function. The review of empirical studies on students' understanding of functions leads to the conclusion that neither reification nor encapsulation is without flaw; however, they have contributed significantly to partially explaining the formation of the function concept. This implies that more theoretical and empirical work needs to be conducted within this area in order for researchers and educators to have a complete explanation of the formation of the function concept.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Functions</subject><subject source="local">Concepts</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_12b90c0fc791774966295d40b160b6c7" level="item"><did><unittitle>Numerical Notation and the Place-Value Concept in Young Children</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00002</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Cayton, Gabrielle A.</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2007-02-02/2007-02-02">2007-02-02</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_a26fd7bcb748dad2e2b54bf86b856e38"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_41cdf535abc230b13c66eaf3feb4e280"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the Doctoral program in MSTE Education. Abstract: In recent decades, we have come to accept that children's appropriation of written numbers is not automatic or simple. Various studies of children's use of notation point to several different types of notational practice possibly linked to stages in the understanding of place value in base-ten (Alvara001, 2002; Brizuela, 2004; Scheuer et al, 2000; Seron &amp; Fayol, 1994). Scheuer et al (2000) discuss two distinct types of incorrect numerical notation strategies used by children: logogramic and compacted notation. Logogramic notation refers to children who write the entire number literally, such as 100701 for one hundred seventy-one. Compacted notation refers to children who remove some of the zeros from the logogramic coding while still not condensing the number entirely into its conventional form, such as 1071 for one hundred seventy-one. Scheuer speculates that perhaps these two types of notational strategies stem from different conceptual ideas about the numbers themselves, yet the study does not explore these ideas, focusing only on written numbers. The study described in this paper examines Scheuer's arguments by comparing numerical notation strategies with children's performance on a task of decomposing numbers created by valued tokens that will provide insights into the children's ideas.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Numerals, Writing of</subject><subject source="local">Children</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_69ac9292ecb95301bdfd2440b048bbf7" level="item"><did><unittitle>Developing Middle School Engineering Teachers: Toward Expertise in Engineering Subject Matter and Pedagogical Content Knowledge</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00003</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Hynes, Morgan M.</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2007-02-01/2007-02-01">2007-02-01</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_c14fddef77ec35bd3d294d2291bc5a18"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_0770a4a558ef269ad533493dcd1148e7"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the program in MSTE Education. Abstract: The purpose of this review is to examine various educational constructs and explore links to developing middle school engineering teachers. In our technical society today, learning and teaching engineering is becoming more and more important.  National and state standards are beginning to include engineering content standards for K-12 classrooms.  If teachers are going to begin teaching engineering they will, undoubtedly, need some preparation before they begin.  In this review, I look at subject matter knowledge, pedagogical knowledge, and expertise and discuss how what has already been done in other fields such as math and science education can be used to inform future development of teaching engineering in the middle school classroom.  Conclusions about how subject matter knowledge and pedagogical content knowledge impact teaching and learning along with insights from expertise literature are used to provide guidance for future research and potential professional development implications.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Engineering - Study and teaching</subject><subject source="local">Education, Elementary</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_e3671dd2339dd238f1ba2d47343b506b" level="item"><did><unittitle>Research Perspectives on the Teaching and Learning of Algebra</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00004</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Martinez, Mara V.</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2008-08-01/2008-08-01">2008-08-01</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_2e239bdf5fa97e3011a59cf9f4b7e54f"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_81251d6e5c62bbb03dddc91b83ebb7db"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Mathematics Education. Abstract: In this paper I will discuss different approaches to algebra adopted by researchers studying teaching and learning of algebra in the last thirty years (1977-2006). For each study reviewed in this paper, the goals are: to identify the central aspects of algebra (for example, algebra as the study of functions or algebra as the study of equation-solving), the mathematical problems researchers propose to use for teaching algebra and for evaluating learning, the used theoretical concepts, and main findings. In addition, I will provide a brief history of the evolution of the field of research on the teaching and learning of algebra, will discuss notions such as the role of equation solving techniques versus meaning making in the teaching and learning of algebra, the relation between arithmetic and algebra, algebra as a modeling tool, and the relation between algebra and proof.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Algebra - Study and teaching</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname><corpname source="local">Tufts University</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_3dfd710375adf814960078844fb787a6" level="item"><did><unittitle>Middle-School Teachers' Use and Development of Engineering Subject Matter and Pedagogical Content Knowledge: A Pilot Study</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00005</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Hynes, Morgan M.</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2008-04-01/2008-04-01">2008-04-01</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_668d8ea2f56a7cb05ed4600ca37fe837"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_1b7d86957e9a4640b89b165c9280c254"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in MSTE Education. Abstract: This paper reports on a study of two middle-school math and one middle-school science teacher as they taught an engineering unit. The study investigated the subject matter knowledge and pedagogical content knowledge these teachers used and developed as they taught an engineering unit that used LEGO to teach students the engineering design process through designing and building an assistive device that uses motors, sensors, and is computer controlled. Data collected from teacher interviews and classroom observations revealed the different subject matter and pedagogical content knowledge the teachers used to teach engineering that was new for them. The data revealed how a teacher's knowledge of physics or engineering can impact their teaching. The data also highlighted that the teachers rarely explicitly used their math or science knowledge to make connections to engineering. The study also illustrated examples of engineering pedagogical content knowledge the teachers developed while teaching the engineering unit. One central conclusion drawn from the study is that teachers would benefit from focused opportunities to develop the different specific types of engineering knowledge that they struggle with the most (i.e., physics concepts, mathematics principles, engineering design). The paper includes a literature review that provides a rationale and framework for studying the teaching of middle-school engineering, a description of the methods used, and results and implications of this study.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Engineering - Study and teaching</subject><subject source="local">Education, Elementary</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_7e94f531632b764f1e0b731c431a6dd3" level="item"><did><unittitle>The Impact of Engineering Education at the Kindergarten to High School Levels: A Review of Research</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00006</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Ortiz, Araceli Martnez</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2008-07-01/2008-07-01">2008-07-01</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_0890724980edcc374eb3f96c046afea5"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_bfc76b7180d41e65c66996411bae9a08"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Engineering Education. Abstract: The aim of this review is to describe a selection of international research efforts in Kindergarten through Grade 12 (K-12) engineering education in order to define an organizing framework for the impact of engineering education on students' development of technological literacy, learning of math and science content, and motivation and understanding of science, technology, engineering, and math (STEM) careers.  A considerable and renewed interest in the field of K-12 engineering education in the United States (US) motivates the need for sharing theoretically grounded research (Benenson, 2001; De Miranda, 2004; Householter, 2000; Norman and Roberts, 2001; Pellegrino, 1999; Zuga, 2000).</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Engineering - Study and teaching</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_e393c1375f349e178909a54eb64b80a5" level="item"><did><unittitle>Integrating Algebra and Proof in High School Students' Work with Algebraic Expressions Involving Variables When Proving</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00007</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Martinez, Mara V.</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2008-05-01/2008-05-01">2008-05-01</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_9b29fd1763fcc2522eba27192ca44283"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_d8f171ddbc97c9c2f1f14a8cc1ec4e40"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Mathematics Education. Abstract: The overarching research question of the study described in this paper is: what are the consequences of an integrated approach to algebra and proof on students' mathematical knowledge while they work through a didactical sequence (i.e., the "Calendar Sequence")?  In particular, the goal of this paper is to report on the challenges that students faced in their work with variables, and equivalent expressions while engaged in producing and proving conjectures, and how these challenges were overcome. Previous studies on algebra and proof (Barallobres, 2004; Bell, 1993) are scant nonetheless promising in regards to students' production of proofs using algebra in an integrated approach. I claim that the results presented in this paper provide promising evidence that an integrated approach towards algebra and proof, such as that implemented in the Calendar Sequence, has a positive impact on students' use of algebra as a tool to prove.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Algebra - Study and teaching</subject><subject source="local">Education, Secondary</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_842aa192b2bab1fadc13ceb3881467fa" level="item"><did><unittitle>Challenges and Promising Approaches in the Teaching and Learning of Introductory Physics at the Secondary Level</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00008</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Crowe, Jacalyn</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2008/2008">2008</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_0ee695b0a0669987b4e7e9b2fdefeebd"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_b26c834d6b06c631a6524a5b13c6afe9"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Science Education. Abstract: The purpose of this review is to identify the challenges facing secondary teachers of physics, to explore the most common instructional methods currently in use and to propose future research that will lean heavily on the use of peer collaboration to foster strong conceptual change.  Through this review, I will argue that: (1) Strong conceptual change or restructuring is needed for high school students to develop as Newtonian thinkers; ( 2) Peer-to-peer verbal interactions may have an important role to play in this process; (3) Combined quantitative and qualitative studies, at the secondary level, are needed to contribute to our understanding of this process for students enrolled in introductory physics courses; and (4) Careful analysis of interaction transcripts will be necessary to inform our understanding of the mechanism involved in conceptual restructuring in this setting.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Physics</subject><subject source="local">Education, Secondary</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_c020f711db20fb27c653a6eb8d886126" level="item"><did><unittitle>The Effect of Structured Peer-to-Peer Interactions on Conceptual Understanding of DC Resistive Circuits in Secondary Physics</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00009</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Crowe, Jacalyn</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2008-06-01/2008-06-01">2008-06-01</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_e88dd52e89c1431284c9ac61675a4469"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_4a413a07cde9c0bb46daf4a30d806872"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Science Education. Abstract: This study examined the prevalence and persistence of some common misconceptions about DC resistive circuits and the role of social interaction in promoting changes in students' views.  It explored the types of interactions that were common in student dialogues as they discussed conceptual questions and whether the number of correct responses to these conceptual questions significantly increased as a result of discussions with peers. Analysis of interactions revealed that the most common student statements during the discussion phase could be characterized as either simply stating their answer or as providing the reasoning behind their answer choice.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Education, Secondary</subject><subject source="local">Physics - Study and teaching</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_6218dd0f5a30d06f69465a28a44953fb" level="item"><did><unittitle>The Theoretical and Empirical Basis for Design-Based Science Instruction for Children</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00010</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Wendell, Kristen B.</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2008-03-24/2008-03-24">2008-03-24</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_e04f510396504287502f77bad2ae17b6"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_2f2bf2fba449db6cee8b2381a2251066"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper. Abstract: My primary goal in this paper is to report comprehensively on the current state of design-based science instruction for children. I will review and synthesize theoretical and empirical literature in an attempt to assist educators, researchers, and developers in their efforts to define effective approaches to design-based science instruction for upper elementary students. My focus is on upper elementary-school students (roughly eight- to eleven-year-olds) because due to their young age, these students are most likely to be influenced by novel instructional activities such as design-based science.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Education, Elementary</subject><subject source="local">Science - Study and teaching</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_ceb0de0533ef8a4df8098e3b3f0a91d6" level="item"><did><unittitle>Learning-By-Teaching as a Pedagogical Approach and Its Implications on Engineering Education</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00011</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Carberry, Adam R.</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2008-07-01/2008-07-01">2008-07-01</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_5318db4d4a188ca7b3b9f1696585b3ca"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_76011157bacf905f9a2aa35ad1e55907"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Math, Science, Technology, and Engineering Education. Abstract: The purpose of the following review is to perform an analysis of what occurs when a student is learning-by-teaching. First, learning-by-teaching will be concretely defined to identify precisely what is meant by the term. Secondly, an analysis of the activities involved in the teaching process will be used to describe why teaching is a beneficial mechanism to elicit learning in the teacher. Theoretical underpinnings associated with such learning approaches will be discussed to construct a framework to support the mechanism. Third, a description of various learning-by-teaching approaches with research support will be shown to describe how learning-by-teaching has been used and what the benefits and drawbacks are to such approaches. Appropriate contexts for use of learning-by-teaching approaches will be included. The concluding discussion will describe the implications that learning-by-teaching can have in engineering education.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Education</subject><subject source="local">Teaching</subject><subject source="local">Engineering</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_e07938281c97e90d1a5a951b807225c6" level="item"><did><unittitle>The science of science education (with a focus of the physics of motion): historical, epistemological, and research contributions. A review of and commentary on literature.</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00012</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Kahn, Jason</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2008-11-01/2008-11-01">2008-11-01</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_56b3c81a51b12dcdb6c72d9e9ec58f81"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_113fc7628a211f1cc8e581bfe69d149a"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper for the Department of Education. Abstract: In an attempt to better understand the field of science education research, the field is reduced to three major contributing disciplines: the practice of science itself as informed through the history of science, developmental psychology and epistemological considerations, and finally the practice of education.  To build an archetypal case, I look exclusively at dynamics, an early pursuit of physics; the lessons could be applied to other branches of science.  In looking at scientific content, it is possible to learn more about the nature of scientific knowledge, and the representational tools that scientists use to generate new knowledge.  This leads to the realization that science in itself is an epistemological tool and raises questions about human development.  In development, we see the processes that individuals employ to gain new knowledge, scientific or otherwise.  Development also provides mechanisms for communities to develop and utilize the same representational tools that are so valuable in creating scientific knowledge.  Finally, the lessons of development must be translated into learning environments.  This typically means classrooms.  Here, researchers and educators have had to maintain a precarious balance between theory and practice, yet there have been several successful results suggesting with a clever approach, excellence in science education is an achievable goal.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Education</subject><subject source="local">Science - Study and teaching</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_0574925a6f473c091ac0ebc018272d6a" level="item"><did><unittitle>Science as Multiple Representations: Integrated perspectives on the role of learning and appropriating representations in constructing science understanding</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00013</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Gravel, Brian E.</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2008/2008">2008</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_8f23360ddf6a3b72aaafd5ebde5742c1"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_2a3926e75fa7e7493bb7b98ea40d959f"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Science Education. Abstract: This work explores how students learn and appropriate representations in the development of understanding.  It is driven by four central questions that address: (1) the reasons for why representation is central to the development of thought; (2) a definition of representation in a manner such that it becomes a useful construct for studying science learning; (3) the evolution of conventional systems of representation and how these attempts to "put the world on paper" have impacted domains of knowledge; and (4) the literature on representation in science specifically from the standpoint of children spontaneously externalizing knowledge across multiple systems.  The integration of theoretical constructs with empirical evidence supports the argument that students must be given opportunities to express themselves in different ways in order to understand science.  Researchers must attend to the relationships between specific systems of representation and conceptual aspects when children engage in scientific discovery.  Finally, this work calls for future research into how spontaneous and idiosyncratic representations of knowledge help students refine explanations and construct scientific understanding.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Science - Study and teaching</subject><subject source="local">Mental representation</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_6f1110c80c09497eb07dba9fdbea960b" level="item"><did><unittitle>Number Concept: Theoretical and Empirical Views of Number Processing</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00014</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Cayton, Gabrielle A.</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2008/2008">2008</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_b059e6ca5a403f98d787edd143bced14"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_d0b1a799908c30bbd57f908ac11e2319"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Mathematics Education. Abstract: Studies of children's numerical understanding over the last decade suggest that there are identifiable progressions in how children develop number concepts.  This paper provides a review of the leading research on number concept and how it relates to the research on external representation of number and number processing models.  It is evident from this review that, while there are many hypotheses surrounding the processing, representation, and interpretation of numbers, much still has to be learned about this subject in young children.  While there are several theories about how children come to understand the number system using various metaphors such as computer programs that learn through experience, currently, the data on young children has yet to provide any conclusive evidence regarding the early childhood number concept and how it gradually develops.  There is a strong need for research in which aspects of the leading number processing theories may apply to children in their acquisition of a full-fledged number concept.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Number concept in children</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_0adfaa247d28880d86cf98c0bd8ccda1" level="item"><did><unittitle>Exploring First Grade Students' Planning in an Engineering Design Problem and Its Relationships to Artifact Construction and Success: A Pilot Study</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00015</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Portsmore, Merridith</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2008-12-01/2008-12-01">2008-12-01</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_8019e53ab897615a9f868cfef8c6007e"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_5b687b3753eabb3eee8b30bff03780be"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Mathematics, Science, Technology, and Engineering Education. Abstract: The purpose of this study was to explore how first grade students plan and solve an engineering design problem.  It specifically analyzes children's drawings of their planned solutions to the problem and how the drawings related to the engineering design problem requirements, the construction of the solutions, and the success of their solutions.  First grade students participated in individual videotaped interview sessions where they engaged in drawing and constructing a solution to an engineering design problem. The results of this study suggest that planning prior to constructing an artifact is something that many first grade students can do but more research is needed to understand the characteristics and experiences of young students that differentiate their performance in planning and carrying ideas from planning to artifact construction.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Education, Elementary</subject><subject source="local">Engineering - Study and teaching</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_8e373d2aee936a7768a4b0383870ab20" level="item"><did><unittitle>Elementary Students' Enhanced Understanding of Perimeter and Area Measurement in an Engineering Contextual Learning Program</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00016</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Ortiz, Araceli Martnez</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2008-12-01/2008-12-01">2008-12-01</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_bff71243d8740c8811159b6b97cac2dc"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_17c860207fb449c6f3ae9975e0afeb1b"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Engineering Education. Abstract: The purpose of this study was to measure the impact of an engineering education afterschool learning program upon elementary students' understanding of perimeter and area measurement.  The study also investigated what activities children attribute to the work of engineers, how they define technology, and how these ideas change after they go through an engineering education afterschool program.  This study, conducted in rural/suburban Massachusetts in 2005, included forty-two elementary students.  Students were voluntarily enrolled in the afterschool program and met during the school year, working collaboratively in a series of ten sessions, eight of which were instructional.  Each student engineering group completed curriculum activities from selected modules of an established elementary program for engineering education while also receiving mathematics instruction on the measurement of perimeter and area.  Student understanding was assessed using a qualitative and quantitative research design.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Education, Elementary</subject><subject source="local">Engineering - Study and teaching</subject><subject source="local">After school programs</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_86e1ddf7f8f1fe482f06db5d8db53aa0" level="item"><did><unittitle>Measuring Engineering Design Self-Efficacy</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00017</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Carberry, Adam R.</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2009-02-01/2009-02-01">2009-02-01</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_23f612749a31150fb64dd951f6cdada6"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_976168b9a4b39b19a62a098c6a084099"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Math, Science, Technology, and Engineering Education. Abstract: The purpose of this study is to take an initial step in the measurement of conative measures, by documenting the development and validation of a new instrument to assess engineering design self-efficacy. Self-efficacy is a motivational construct regarding an individuals belief or judgment of their capability to organize and execute courses of action for a given domain-specific task (Bandura, 1986, 1997). Self-efficacy influences behaviors in accordance with perceived abilities for a specific task. The task of interest for this study will be engineering design. Engineering design is the process used to devise a system, component, or process to meet a need. The concept was chosen because of its importance in the field of engineering (Auyang, 2004).</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Engineering - Study and teaching</subject><subject source="local">Education</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_f706e2eb9a61cc31d366d1531f04a398" level="item"><did><unittitle>The Effect of Two-Dimensional and Stereoscopic Presentation on Middle School Students' Performance of Spatial Cognition Tasks</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00018</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Price, Aaron</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2009/2009">2009</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_281a42a6235235c6311a67d33a127de9"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_3b10e095d7ab060c5461b45b3dd7772c"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree in Mathematics, Science, Technology, and Engineering Education. Abstract: Nineteen middle-school aged students visiting a planetarium were presented with three types of spatial cognition tasks using both two-dimensional (flat) and stereoscopic representations. The students' performance on tasks was evaluated in order to determine the impact of stereoscopic presentation upon accuracy and task completion time. Results show that accuracy did not differ between the two representational types while completion time was greater for the stereoscopic representations. Post task interviews show that students continued to think of the stereoscopic spatial tasks as two-dimensional. Results were analyzed through the lenses of cognitive load and cue theory.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Education, Elementary</subject><subject source="local">Cognition</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_6679ca5cda233e82da7d861f6664b2e9" level="item"><did><unittitle>Toward a More Complete Theory of Design-Based Science Teaching and Learning: Recognizing the Voices of Students of Color</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00019</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Wright, Christopher G.</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2009/2009">2009</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_31a24ee9d3c927773b568d1614a799e4"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_646ec5172b310b4f58f0cde01e921cfa"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Engineering Education. Abstract: The aim of this review is to explore the question of whose Discursive practices count within primary science education and science education research. To examine this question, this review situates science Discursive practices within the dichotomous relationship of dominant and non-dominant and uses these categories to theorize, examine, and challenge the ways that race and racism implicitly and explicitly impact school views of scientific thinking and knowledge. The goal of this exploration is to advocate for the implementation of alternative methods of study and analysis when investigating the Discursive practices of children from communities of color, particularly within the context of design-based science activities. With the increased recognition of design-based science as a pedagogical approach to teaching science, I contend that the experiences of all children need to be investigated in order to develop a more complete theory of design-based science teaching and learning. Designing explorations into what these children bring to design-based science activities will assist in the process of ensuring academic success for all students.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Science - Study and teaching</subject><subject source="local">Race</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_7c80ab861b1c697db40d67933ced885d" level="item"><did><unittitle>Children's Understanding of Area of Rectangular Regions and Volumes of Rectangular Shapes and the Relationship of These Measures to Their Linear Dimensions</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00020</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Martin, Joan D.</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2007-04-01/2007-04-01">2007-04-01</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_f82d0b39a9032cea38c7e2c94d8b3fa0"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_ccb7f3cb8c31e416ea4eeb7a2be69374"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Math, Science, Technology, and Engineering Education. Abstract: What is needed to strengthen our students' understanding of the attributes of space, to prepare our students for a world that requires increasingly advanced levels of technical sophistications?  Again the questions posed are: which concepts should be taught and when should these concepts be introduced? Are there particular sequences or an order in which these concepts should be taught?  And what materials and tools should be used in the teaching and learning of geometry? In seeking to answer the above questions, this paper focuses on a narrower band of geometric measurement, aimed at harvesting the findings of the reviewed research and  suggesting fruitful possibilities for further study. The main goal is to review the literature on studies that have been conducted specifically in the treatment of area and volume, as well as length, with elementary students.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Geometry - Study and teaching</subject><subject source="local">Education, Elementary</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_7c0490db0938f5baf457382619bf9a61" level="item"><did><unittitle>Exploratory study of fourth graders concurrently investigating perimeter, area, surface area, and volume in an interactive classroom</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00021</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Martin, Joan D.</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2007-07-01/2007-07-01">2007-07-01</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_00b33a9eb68002722d77c2c559c3e8ed"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_caf659610f9feffe2c3cea5c0449fc7d"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Math, Science, Technology, and Engineering Education. Abstract: This paper describes an exploratory study of how a fourth grade class investigated the relationships among perimeter, area, surface area, and volume of rectangular shapes. The five-session intervention involved 11 boys and 8 girls in a suburban public school. The students working independently and in partnerships were given particular tools (e.g., measuring strings, grid mats, rectangular prisms, pre-cut rectangular shapes, one-inch plastic tiles, and Klick-like puzzles) to complete measurement tasks. The students demonstrated their understanding of the 2-D and 3-D attributes in pretests and posttests, discussions, reflections, prediction tasks, constructions of 2-D and 3-D rectangular shapes and arrays, and posters. The quantitative results indicate increased student performance and understanding, particularly for area, surface area, volume, and appropriate units of spatial measure. Qualitative findings suggest that the interaction of planned partnerships, the materials students used, and the tasks, activities, and reflections they completed, produced positive results.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Geometry - Study and teaching</subject><subject source="local">Education, Elementary</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_dbe825fe088459ee0765963a861c0cab" level="item"><did><unittitle>The relationships between teacher and student understanding: The conceptual field of combinatorics</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00022</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Caddle, Mary</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2009-06-02/2009-06-02">2009-06-02</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_1219240df844eca27d3787d03603f5c4"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_8ebcd339abdfa3e8adc0dcfdf6346cf9"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Math, Science, Technology, and Engineering Education. Abstract: The purpose of this review is to build a foundation from which to consider the relationships among the professional development activities of middle and secondary school mathematics teachers, the mathematical understanding and pedagogical content knowledge of the teachers, and the mathematical understanding of their students.  The goal is to enable investigation of the following questions: What are the relationships among: (i)	a teacher's understanding in combinatorics; (ii) the teacher's pedagogical content knowledge in combinatorics; (iii) their students' understanding in combinatorics? Specifically, what is the relationship between the ways in which a teacher is able to solve and explain introductory problems in combinatorics and the ways in which their students respond to similar problems?  Are there connections between a teacher's mathematical understanding and their students' mathematical understanding?</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Mathematics - Study and teaching</subject><subject source="local">Education, Secondary</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_b922d9eff84ea976559797b5a223f685" level="item"><did><unittitle>Students' and teachers' understandings of mathematical functions</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00023</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Burnett-Bradshaw, Camille S.</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2011-02-01/2011-02-01">2011-02-01</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_509c66ca59ac3e0fa65929904486f817"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_19ace650946a92548b37c3b5255e5a7e"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Math, Science, Technology, and Engineering Education. Abstract: The goal of the study presented in this paper is to describe students' and teachers' understandings of: (1) the definition of function and (2) the transformations of functions in different representations.  This will be achieved through a case study analysis of two ninth grade students, two twelfth grade students, and two mathematics teachers.  The six participants were recruited from the same high school in Boston, Massachusetts, which serves a diverse racial, ethnic, and cultural community.  The participants were interviewed individually about questions pertaining to the definition of function and the transformations of functions.  Analysis of the results revealed that the ninth grade students have a less sophisticated understanding of the concept of function than do twelfth grade students.  It was expected that both teachers would have a similar understanding of functions, but it was found that the twelfth grade teacher had a more theoretical and rigid understanding of the concept of function than did the ninth grade teacher, who had a more practical and flexible understanding of the concept of function.  In this case, flexible means translating to other representations of functions and/or using different approaches to functions, while rigid means the opposite.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Mathematics - Study and teaching</subject><subject source="local">Education, Secondary</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_256485e6f2948f6de4fd62744a479b13" level="item"><did><unittitle>Analyzing solution methods for combinatorics problems: differences across problems and across teachers</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00024</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Caddle, Mary</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2010/2010">2010</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_90d3208de17184adbc9f95552f8f9c7c"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_6296bd0435dcc4c485b14059680694b3"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Math, Science, Technology, and Engineering Education. Abstract: This paper describes a small study in which five teachers were interviewed in order to gain insight into their understanding of combinatorics.  Combinatorics is a challenging mathematical area that provides learners with a basis for a great deal of applied mathematics, including statistics.  Through interviews with teachers, this study sought to investigate how the teachers solved combinatorics problems, the methods they used, the issues they raised, and the knowledge they displayed.In particular, the analysis presented here addresses three questions:i.	how do the methods used when solving combinatorics problems relate to the mathematical attributes of the question;ii.	how do the methods used when solving combinatorics problems in an interview differ across teachers;iii.	how does a mathematical problem with unexpected difficulties or subtleties illuminate the differences among teachers.In order to address these questions, this paper will first look at the reasons for focusing on this area of mathematics and will define the specific area that I am addressing.  Next, we will look at existing work on teaching and learning combinatorics, including considering some common errors and misconceptions.Following this, the methodology for this study will be described.   The methodology section will describe the line-by-line analysis of the transcripts of the teacher interviews, during which each participant was asked to solve and discuss a series of combinatorics problems. The results from this analysis regarding the relationships among teachers, methods, and mathematical tasks are outlined in detail.The subsequent discussion provides both a qualitative look at these first two research questions and a foundation and justification for addressing the third research question, (iii) how does a mathematical problem with unexpected difficulties or subtleties illuminate the differences among teachers.  The discussion shows that the differences among teachers extend beyond which methods they choose and whether or not the answers to the questions are simply correct or incorrect, but also include subtleties in how they employ the methods and how they view the utility of each one.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Mathematics - Study and teaching</subject><subject source="local">Mathematics teachers</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_20914934a6adb8b9f19692da8f560258" level="item"><did><unittitle>Children's materials science practices before, during, and after a design-based science learning experience</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00025</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Wendell, Kristen B.</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2009/2009">2009</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_f3abfb649180319251d1d6f7ac8ab0ac"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_9bb71119e412ea7c988d1678f19abb2c"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Math, Science, Technology, and Engineering Education. Abstract: Materials science, which entails the practices of selecting, testing, and characterizing materials, is an important discipline within the study of matter. This paper examines how third grade students' materials science performance changes over the course of instruction based on an engineering design challenge. I conducted a case study of nine students who participated in engineering design-based science instruction with the goal of constructing a stable, quiet, thermally comfortable model house. The learning outcome of materials science practices was assessed by clinical interviews conducted before and after the instruction, and the learning process was assessed by students' workbooks completed during the instruction. The interviews included two materials selection tasks for designing a sturdy stepstool and an insulated pet habitat. Results indicate that (1) students significantly improved on both materials selection tasks, (2) their gains were significantly positively associated with the degree of completion of their workbooks, and (3) students who were highly engaged with the workbook's reflective record-keeping tasks showed the greatest improvement on the interviews. These findings suggest the important role workbooks can play in facilitating elementary students' learning of science through authentic activity such as engineering design.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Teaching - methods</subject><subject source="local">Science - Study and teaching</subject><subject source="local">Education, Elementary</subject><corpname source="local">Dept. of Education</corpname></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_0a1e1d004bde6bd97360ff928b5ad9fb" level="item"><did><unittitle>A ten-year-old child's representations of motion</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00026</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Kendall, Amber</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2012/2012">2012</unitdate><abstract id="aspace_a9499d0b3f97e2ca6ed36c296baab176">This paper presents the case study of a 10-year-old boy and the various representations he produces to express his ideas about the motion of a car through three clinical interviews.  This work also provides an initial exploration of using animation (SAM Animation software, http://www.samanimation.com) as an alternative to conventional graphing in the elementary classroom, to quantitatively represent understandings of motion in a form closer to children's spontaneous figurative drawing.  The goals of this study were to explore the invented representations of motion produced by a 10 year old boy; how his paper and pencil representations compared to those produced through animations; and how his understandings of time, displacement, speed, and acceleration were expressed through the representations he created.  Two types of drawings (figurative and non-figurative) and one animation of the motion of a car produced by an elementary student were examined to compare the resources used in their creation and the ways in which they allowed me to explore the students' understandings of motion.  Many resources previously observed in other students' works, such as drawings, words, "more is more," temporal sequences, and line segments were present in all three types of representation.  The figurative drawings exhibited rudimentary understandings of motion, representing changes in the car's speed as snapshots rather than continuous accelerations.  The non-figurative representations depicted slightly more quantitative information about speed and acceleration using almost the same set of resources, but incorporating the idea of acceleration as changing speed.  The child recognized the potential for demonstrating "real life" motion within the medium of animation, but his actual product shared more similarities with the resources of the static figurative drawings that he had produced than his non-figurative representations, in which he represented quantities more explicitly.  However, the animation's explicit treatment of time, and small ___t, provided the basis for the exploration of the "A x B = C" relationships between speed, displacement, and duration, and speed, acceleration and duration.  The three forms of representation provided for varied contexts through which his understandings of speed, time, and acceleration articulated in the drawings could be explored in the resulting discussions about his productions.</abstract><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_d3896c1cac137bcd1bf73f90c0eea117"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict></c><c id="aspace_27b9f05d660eb4d44479c908e79dff8a" level="item"><did><unittitle>What Is Speed: A Young Chinese Adult Non-Scientist's Epistemologies and Her Understandings of Speed</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00027</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Cao, Ying</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2012/2012">2012</unitdate><abstract id="aspace_436223aba5fcf1068c6ce7aae096c3a4">In science education studies, researchers have thoroughly investigated the epistemologies held by students who are learning science. These research findings, however, have yet to be applied to individuals who are not currently enrolled in science classes. Additionally, these studies have primarily focused on individuals from Western cultures and who are native English speakers. In this paper I examine an individual to see whether the research claims in relation to students' epistemologies still apply to someone with different characteristics. Overall, I aimed to investigate whether Hammer and colleagues' claims concerning learners' epistemologies (e.g., Hammer, 1994; Hammer, Elby, Scherr, &amp; Redish, 2005) can be more widely applied than their previous research has indicated by extending these claims to individuals who lack advanced science training, have had different learning experiences, and who grew up speaking and learning in another language and culture. The findings show that previous theoretical frameworks can be used to explain the epistemologies of the individual examined in this study. The case suggests that these theories may apply to individuals regardless of the learner's science background, language, education experience, and cultural background. More cases should be examined with learners with different academic backgrounds and from different cultures if we want to provide more compelling evidence for this claim.</abstract><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_a9c122b089967095483dcd09d00a3989"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict></c><c id="aspace_559f9ed95900be1be895feeb957bb268" level="item"><did><unittitle>Affect and the scientific pursuit: Learning to feel like a scientist</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00028</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Jaber, Lama Ziad</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2013-07-23/2013-07-23">2013-07-23</unitdate><abstract id="aspace_26921e9285341c50e18fcbae3851da91">This paper argues that affect is central to scientific pursuits and to engaging in science conceptually and epistemologically. To ground this claim, we first review accounts of scientists' intellectual practices that suggest that science involves the activation and refinement of affective resources, such as excitement for figuring things out, annoyance at inconsistencies, empathy with the object of inquiry, and persistence in the face of challenges. We then discuss a case study from a fourth grade science classroom which shows that (1) science learners can experience disciplinary feelings and emotions similar to those of scientists; (2) these affective experiences are closely entwined with the conceptual and epistemological substance of student engagement; and (3) they are consequential to the nature and flow of inquiry. Affect, we contend, is part and parcel of scientific pursuits, and learning science is in part learning how to feel like a scientist. We conclude with some implications of this perspective on research and instruction.</abstract><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_6b11b638c8b1485086c3aa19cf6f2116"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_4b28a817c003dfe5c7ff7c93dbc30e8d"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy In Science Education.</p></scopecontent></c><c id="aspace_f6b256bb7dd904b73b8c2c6144bda32f" level="item"><did><unittitle>Attending to Affect in Student Inquiry</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00029</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Jaber, Lama Z.</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2014/2014">2014</unitdate><abstract id="aspace_31642e753e430d11602ba97667650c38">This paper explores dynamics of attending and responding to affect as integral to, rather than separate from, attending to the substance of students" ideas. I examine the relationship between responsiveness to affect and the disciplinary substance of student thinking. The questions I consider are: how does a teacher attend and respond to affect as integral to the substance of student reasoning and ideas in the science class? And how do these acts of attending
                                and responding become consequential to student engagement? Using a case study of a fifth grade teacher's interactions with a student struggling to communicate an idea, I illustrate how the teacher's attention and responsiveness to affect was an act of attending to the student's reasoning and persistence. Moreover, I show how intending for his student to struggle at the intellectual level was an act of caring for him as an intellectual agent. In this way, I show
                                how caring can be connected to and in service of student disciplinary engagement and epistemic agency. More broadly, I highlight the need to examine affect as inherent to the discipline in conversations on responsive teaching and I discuss implications on instruction and teacher education.</abstract><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_7ded5b0bd67996b10351efe77f3baab6"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_b6619742968337cd3851fbf228b12c27"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Education.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Department of Education records.</subject><subject source="local">Teachers--Psychology.</subject><subject source="local">Teacher-student relationships.</subject><subject source="local">Teachers--Attitudes.</subject><subject source="local">Affect (Psychology)</subject></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_8cb671e13507117c74cac3101aed742e" level="item"><did><unittitle>Attention to Student Framing in Responsive Teaching</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00030</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Radoff, Jennifer A.</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2014/2014">2014</unitdate><abstract id="aspace_91256b08fb3e21e51e408df951ff8fef">A central issue of responsive teaching involves how teachers decide, tacitly or explicitly, to distribute their attention in the classroom. Even within the narrow realm of attending and responding to the substance of student thinking, teachers must constantly make decisions about what student thinking to pursue and how to pursue it. In this paper, we explore a third-grade teacher's shift in the scope of her attention, from a wider consideration of the class's
                                sense of what they are doing"their epistemological framing"to a more narrow consideration of the conceptual substance of particular ideas. We claim that a key factor influencing the teacher's scoping of attention is her sense of the stability of students" framing.</abstract><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_cffc96c01feebb0318d0fee25df474b2"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_9052fe7f3a70b3e34e68e2a288e85eb7"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Education</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Department of Education records.</subject><subject source="local">Teachers--Psychology.</subject><subject source="local">Teacher-student relationships.</subject><subject source="local">Teachers--Attitudes.</subject></controlaccess></c><c id="aspace_e8f61d19d0b8658c0b97830730276c26" level="item"><did><unittitle>High School Students' Understandings and Representations of the Electric Field</unittitle><unitid>UA071.001.001.00031</unitid><origination label="Creator"><persname source="local">Cao, Ying</persname></origination><unitdate normal="2014/2014">2014</unitdate><abstract id="aspace_1e177e27b31d0c024bcbc0f93c8386d7">This study investigates the understandings and representations of the electric field expressed by Chinese high school students ages 15 to 16 who have not yet received high school-level physics instruction. The literature has reported students' ideas of the electric field post-instruction as indicated by their performance on textbook-style questionnaires. However, by relying on measures such as questionnaires, previous research has inadequately captured the thinking process that led students to answer questions in the ways that they did. The present study portrays the beginning of this process by closely examining students' understandings pre-instruction. The participants in this study were asked to engage in a lesson that included informal group tasks that involved playing a Web-based hockey game that replicated an electric field and drawing comic strips that used charges as characters. The lesson was videotaped, students' work was collected, and three students
                were interviewed afterward to ascertain more detail about their work. I identified nine ideas related to the electric field that students spontaneously leveraged, even though they had yet to receive formal instruction on the topic. In this paper, I will discuss my findings in comparison with previous research claims.</abstract><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_278852c29f7c4962a3079dfdd8a11e4a"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_b55aac82127ce7d0bd3c0396d8544ea0"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Education.</p></scopecontent><controlaccess><subject source="local">Department of Education records.</subject><subject source="local">Tufts University. Department of Education</subject><subject source="local">Electric fields--Study and teaching (Secondary)</subject></controlaccess></c></c><c id="aspace_3bbc74b2ccff7d5e90f8fc73062015c8" level="series"><did><unittitle>Additional accessions</unittitle><unitid>UA071.002</unitid></did><c id="aspace_d8552c24fa72f7026fa0b6c1df63da62" level="file"><did><unittitle>Liberal Arts Education box</unittitle><unitid>UA071.002.002</unitid><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container id="aspace_c7d3ef8685b375d59ae0ff2ded7c9e22" label="Mixed Materials [39090015752815g]" type="box">data_value_missing_ce64662cf04bbc2baabf3e112b542184</container><container id="aspace_3dae8ba2fe2a97eb96c21d50e953deca" label="Mixed Materials [39090017907094]" type="box">2</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_5918335e91b7046c15903add54bd882a"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict></c></c><c id="aspace_de68da87b21eb7387f00807f6c16d699" level="series"><did><unittitle>2017 accessions</unittitle><unitid>UA071.003</unitid><physdesc altrender="whole"><extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">.1 Linear Feet</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1954/1954">1954</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_4ffd556b1a3fb0b67874343347898544"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>This series is open for research.</p></accessrestrict><acqinfo id="aspace_1fcb829fff32c21a1ecf875af2e504ef"><head>Immediate Source of Acquisition</head><p>Gift of Lawrence Rudd, 2017, accession UA-2018-027.</p></acqinfo><arrangement id="aspace_0101f4357ebe780b0e63068e11e90e9e"><head>Arrangement</head><p>This series is arranged in received order.</p></arrangement><scopecontent id="aspace_3c748ab4f14de5252da9372463be8156"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>This series contains one slide box of color slides taken by Lonie Rudd at an outdoor education camp for Tufts School of Education students in 1954. The slides may have been taken by or belonged to Bradley Palmer, who taught math education.</p></scopecontent><custodhist id="aspace_f2c35dd0b3c0692adc071844d0081365"><head>Custodial History</head><p>These slides were gifted by Lawrence Rudd to the Tufts University Office of Alumni Relations in November 2017. This office donated the slides to DCA in December 2017.</p></custodhist><c id="aspace_501ccfc9c7353ff2f7581dfd40e8a624" level="file"><did><unittitle>Outdoor education camp slides</unittitle><unitid>UA071.003.002.00001</unitid><physdesc altrender="whole"><extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">.1 Linear Feet</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1954/1954">1954</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container id="aspace_3256406e1f5adc84d5d66a435840b9e7" label="Graphic Materials [39090015752815g]" type="box">data_value_missing_ce64662cf04bbc2baabf3e112b542184</container><container id="aspace_cdb0ae0638e1af62af8ddc62c3060fd5" label="Mixed Materials [39090017907094]" type="box">2</container></did></c></c></dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
