<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd"><eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" findaidstatus="under_revision" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511"><eadid countrycode="US" url="http://hdl.handle.net/10427/48342">UA183</eadid><filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper>Jonathan M. Tisch College of Civic Life Records<num>UA183</num></titleproper></titlestmt><publicationstmt><publisher>Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University</publisher><p id="logostmt"><extref xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:href="https://dca.tufts.edu/themes/custom/dca_foundation/images/logos/full_with_icon.svg" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple"/></p><address><addressline>35 Professors Row</addressline><addressline>Tisch Library Building</addressline><addressline>Tufts University</addressline><addressline>Medford, Massachusetts 02155</addressline><addressline>archives@tufts.edu</addressline><addressline>URL: <extptr xlink:href="https://dca.tufts.edu/" xlink:show="new" xlink:title="https://dca.tufts.edu/" xlink:type="simple"/></addressline></address></publicationstmt></filedesc><profiledesc><creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on <date>2021-10-29 15:48:27 -0400</date>.</creation></profiledesc></eadheader><archdesc level="collection">
  <did>
    <repository>
      <corpname>Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University</corpname>
    </repository>
    <unittitle>Jonathan M. Tisch College of Civic Life Records</unittitle>
    <origination label="Creator">
      <corpname source="local">Lincoln Filene Center (1961-1999)</corpname>
    </origination>
    <origination label="Creator">
      <corpname source="local">University College</corpname>
    </origination>
    <origination label="Creator">
      <corpname source="local">Tufts University Art Gallery</corpname>
    </origination>
    <origination label="Creator">
      <corpname source="local">Lincoln Filene Center (2002- )</corpname>
    </origination>
    <origination label="Creator">
      <persname source="local">O'Connell, Brian</persname>
    </origination>
    <origination label="Creator">
      <persname source="local">Hollister, Robert</persname>
    </origination>
    <origination label="Creator">
      <corpname source="local">University College of Citizenship and Public Service</corpname>
    </origination>
    <unitid>UA183</unitid>
    <physdesc altrender="whole">
      <extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">14.95 Linear Feet</extent>
      <extent altrender="carrier">14 boxes</extent>
    </physdesc>
    <unitdate normal="1975/2018" type="inclusive">1975 -- 2018</unitdate>
    <abstract id="aspace_dd662f0f15c3a3262b088f3ae3feffb3">This collection contains records created by the Jonathan M. Tisch College of Civic Life as well as records created by related predecessor groups such as the Lincoln Filene Center.</abstract>
    <langmaterial>
      <language langcode="eng">English</language>
.    </langmaterial>
  </did>
  <accessrestrict id="aspace_46d955a2d8a338f02c9a248f1fce4553">
    <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
<p>This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.</p>  </accessrestrict>
  <acqinfo id="aspace_fb8324e20b78700cfbd6af20b99d9d9a">
    <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition</head>
<p>Transferred by Jonathan M. Tisch College of Civic Life, 2006 -- 2016.</p>  </acqinfo>
  <arrangement id="aspace_e079a7ac73b8fb408cf04cbaa36ed646">
    <head>Arrangement</head>
<p>This collection is organized in two series: University College of Citizenship and Public Service records and Unprocessed accessions.</p>  </arrangement>
  <bioghist id="aspace_5088f70bf2d562998e6356e5080c54b8">
    <head>Biographical / Historical</head>
<p>The Jonathan M. Tisch College of Civic Life was founded in the year 2000, after deliberation by a team led by President DiBiaggio on how best to prepare students for "lifetimes of active citizenship."  Originally called the University College of Citizenship and Public Service, the school was renamed in 2006 as the Jonathan M. Tisch College of Citizenship and Public Service after a $40 million gift from Jonathan Tisch.  The College was renamed the Jonathan M. Tisch College of Civic Life in 2016, to better indicate the school's objective of "encouraging civic engagement in all parts of life."   
The University College of Citizenship and Public Service arose out of Tufts' long history with the Civic Education Foundation and the Lincoln and Therese Filene Foundation. In the early 1950s, President Wessell took notice of the Civic Education Foundation and the Civic Education Project. By 1954 the Foundation had come to an agreement with Wessell to relocate the Project on Tufts campus, and update its name to the "Tufts College Center for Civic Education in Cooperation with the Civic Education Foundation." It was designated to be separate from the university, so that it could function independently of any specific faculty or department, yet have the ability to "interact freely" with all parts of Tufts, as well as the surrounding community.   
During this time, the Lincoln and Therese Filene Foundation also showed growing interest in contributing to the Tufts community. In the mid-1950s, the Foundation endowed the Lincoln and Therese Filene Professorship in Citizenship and Public Affairs, and worked with Tufts student Richard Dorsay to create the Leonard Carmichael Society, a student community service organization.  In 1961, the Filene Foundation provided funds for the Tufts College Center for Civic Education to become the Lincoln Filene Center for Citizenship and Public Affairs.  The Filene Foundation also allocated funds for the Lincoln Filene Center building to be built as an extension of Braker Hall. With this new construction, the Civic Education Foundation was able to run its operations from Tufts, and found that the location was ideal for close communication with the university.  
Though the Center was intended to be a nonprofit organization independent of the university, the trustee bylaws from 1962 to 1975 referred to the Center as a part of the university, causing the Center to reassert its independence in 1973, with changes to the bylaws completed in 1975.  The Center merged with the Tufts Center for Public Service in 1988, due to financial problems with the Center that also resulted in the disbandment of the Civic Education Foundation. However, though this event marked the Lincoln Filene Center's official integration into Tufts, Tufts continued to expand the Center's programs under its initial name.      
In 1998, President DiBiaggio began to investigate with a team how to best incorporate active citizenship into the Tufts curriculum. Inspired by the Tufts Public Service Council, DiBiaggio proposed the University College of Citizenship and Public Service, and worked with Filene Center director Badi Foster to strengthen the Lincoln Filene Center's involvement. The aim of chartering the school was to advance the work already done by the Tufts Public Service Council and the Lincoln Filene Center. Though proponents of the College did not set out to replace the Lincoln Filene Center, they sought to build on the Center's initial mission of civic engagement and involve more of the Tufts community.  The trustees approved the establishment of the University College in November of 1999, and it started its first academic year in the fall of 2000.   
The College has received numerous gifts over the years for support. The College initially relied on a gift from Tufts alumni Pam and Pierre Omidyar to develop the college and its curriculum.  Jonathan Tisch made gifts to the school in 2006 and 2016 respectively, resulting in the College updating its name to reflect his involvement. Rob Hollister served as the first dean of the college, appointed by the trustees in the spring of 2000. He stepped down from this position in 2011, leaving Nancy Wilson to serve as Dean ad interim. In 2014, Alan Solomont was named Dean of Tisch College.  
Tisch College offers numerous programs to fulfill its mission of incorporating active citizenship into the Tufts curriculum.  In its early years, the College sponsored the Omidyar Scholars program, a program where undergraduate students received leadership training to promote societal awareness and civic participation.  Additionally, the College has sponsored an honor society for graduate students and a bridge-year service program for incoming undergraduates. The College also houses the Center for Information and Research on Civic Learning and Engagement, and the Institute for Democracy and Higher Education, two organizations dedicated to researching civic engagement and participation.</p>  </bioghist>
  <prefercite id="aspace_3b56c49a6396dab0274165283ea7cb99">
    <head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>Jonathan M. Tisch College of Civic Life Records, 1975 -- 2012. Tufts University. Digital Collections and Archives. Medford, MA.</p>  </prefercite>
  <processinfo id="aspace_435c6bc5b89b3dd12c0046d17920335d">
    <head>Processing Information</head>
<p>Preliminary processing of Brian O'Connell files completed by Leah Edelman in 2017. Materials were placed in archival boxes if the orignal housing was damaged, and loose materials were placed in folders. Received order was maintained. A box-level inventory was created and the finding aid was updated at the time of preliminary processing.  </p>  </processinfo>
  <scopecontent id="aspace_9dad5434f6693e8110bdfe338c876904">
    <head>Scope and Contents</head>
<p>This collection contains records created by the Jonathan M. Tisch College of Civic Life as well as records created by related predecessor groups such as the Lincoln Filene Center. Records include files of Dean Robert Hollister and of professor Brian O'Connell, as well as scrapbooks, financial information, videos, program information, publications, reports, subject files, and grant applications. Significant topics in this collection include The Talloires Network conferences and seminars, the MacJannet Foundation, and the Mystic River Watershed Association.</p>  </scopecontent>
  <processinfo id="aspace_47510b923fa8f8a3281500059632b33c">
    <head>Processing status</head>
<p>This collection is partially processed.</p>  </processinfo>
  <userestrict id="aspace_f747eebf92f3cb4ead93f04f8514547b">
    <head>Conditions Governing Use</head>
<p>Some material in this collection may be protected by copyright and other rights. Please see "Reproductions and Use" on the Digital Collections and Archives website for more information about reproductions and permission to publish. Copyright to all materials created by Tufts University employees in the course of their work is held by the Trustees of Tufts University.</p>  </userestrict>
  <controlaccess>
    <subject source="local">Curriculum and Instruction</subject>
    <subject source="local">Curriculum and Instruction -- Faculty</subject>
    <subject source="local">Advancement</subject>
  </controlaccess>
  <dsc><c id="aspace_a082ae33f03550996954d01a73198ac9" level="series"><did><unittitle>University College of Citizenship and Public Service records</unittitle><unitid>UA183.001</unitid><physdesc altrender="whole"><extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">2.4 Linear Feet</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1975/2018" type="inclusive">1975 -- 2018</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><scopecontent id="aspace_92f4aa7149afc89d66f95090da0c2ada"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>This series contains material publshed by the University College of Citizenship and Public Service, as well as the files of Brian O'Connell (A'53, Tufts trustee, professor of citizenship and public service, and Tisch College board member).</p></scopecontent><accessrestrict id="aspace_72c524e78134c380b6d92194c7ebbf1a"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>This series is open for research.</p></accessrestrict><arrangement id="aspace_4691ecbc660c08b731a99be1b60f0bab"><head>Arrangement</head><p>This series is arranged in order of accession.</p></arrangement><c id="aspace_17c37ab7a479377c9661ad6dd09de341" level="file"><did><unittitle>Brian O'Connell files</unittitle><unitid>UA183.001.013</unitid><physdesc altrender="whole"><extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">1.8 Linear Feet</extent><extent altrender="carrier">1 record carton and 1 document box</extent></physdesc><unitdate certainty="approximate" normal="1975/2006" type="inclusive">circa 1975 -- 2006</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container id="aspace_33154ec034f95cc337417f70d6ec4dfa" label="Mixed Materials [39090017907722]" type="box">13</container><container id="aspace_94e54c2b3f0c23622480ce4111f45cfb" label="Mixed Materials [39090017908092]" type="box">14</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_d3a62ccab19e2b3b1d941e68bb525fe0"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><acqinfo id="aspace_72c9a86ff10a27a4a61655efe646d76b"><head>Immediate Source of Acquisition</head><p>Transferred by Robert Hollister of Tisch College, 2016, accession UA-2017-013.</p></acqinfo><scopecontent id="aspace_d13e1748fd8c020ae9467f35b1ca83d8"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>These files consist of articles, speeches, interviews, and other publications on topics including religion, philanthropy, government and independent sector relations, advocacy, civil society, and altruism. Files include writings of Brian O'Connell (A'53, Tufts trustee, professor of citizenship and public service, and Tisch College board member), as well as publications by others kept as research material.</p></scopecontent></c><c id="aspace_eb70780ed92d9bb7cc152e03ab92069e" level="file"><did><unittitle>Publications</unittitle><unitid>UA183.001.014.00001</unitid><physdesc altrender="whole"><extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">1 Folder(s)</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="2018/2018" type="inclusive">circa 2018</unitdate><container id="aspace_801a9bf2f545fd3f2a90cd38f5a21cc4" label="Mixed Materials [39090011509922]" type="box">15</container><container id="aspace_4dcaaf3963e246cd180ffbd27f2441ce" parent="aspace_801a9bf2f545fd3f2a90cd38f5a21cc4" type="folder">1</container></did></c></c><c id="aspace_2629999ce34744830c385be92e8a07b9" level="series"><did><unittitle>Additional accessions</unittitle><unitid>UA183.002</unitid><unitdate normal="1975/2012" type="inclusive">1975 -- 2012</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><c id="aspace_9b24125af0e2a29a5abb3ebc6a9f39e2" level="file"><did><unittitle>UCCPS brochures, planning, annual report, photos</unittitle><unitid>UA183-001</unitid><unitdate certainty="approximate" normal="1999/2012" type="inclusive">1999 -- 2012</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container id="aspace_654fdf87fc61d21ad698115d56717505" label="Mixed Materials [39090017918810]" type="box">1</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_a253997e3026ee80bfa22d82242ec926"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>20 years from date of creation.</p></accessrestrict></c><c id="aspace_cbcc89544694b6d9259b2638d015d954" level="file"><did><unittitle>Dean Robert Hollister's Files</unittitle><unitid>UA183-002</unitid><unitdate certainty="approximate" normal="1994/2005" type="inclusive">1994 -- 2005</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container id="aspace_0015b7f28ea13a44e4193716ae660a13" label="Mixed Materials [39090017918828]" type="box">2</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_e11edf1398dc74b33cf9ca194e1dfbc3"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>20 years from date of creation.</p></accessrestrict></c><c id="aspace_a082dfd3ca90b943e02d2fa39312192a" level="file"><did><unittitle>Dean Robert Hollister's Files</unittitle><unitid>UA183-003</unitid><unitdate certainty="approximate" normal="2000/2000">2000</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container id="aspace_e469863556106c479f9a2dd06dbf93c6" label="Mixed Materials [39090017918836]" type="box">3</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_45044f5bea336463c05bb1021ff94f82"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>20 years from date of creation.</p></accessrestrict></c><c id="aspace_badcc63919675aa9871fa94cce625cf9" level="file"><did><unittitle>University College of Citizenship and Public Service scrapbooks</unittitle><unitid>UA183-004</unitid><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container id="aspace_619219cf421b08cac4f1b6fc27a89922" label="Mixed Materials [39090017918844]" type="box">4</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_fd8842fbc9da35ee1c3d2d0d2161ed5f"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>20 years from date of creation.</p></accessrestrict></c><c id="aspace_6d145c503a27e7b4f95e9f9e0e2a5870" level="file"><did><unittitle>University College of Citizenship and Public Service </unittitle><unitid>UA183-005</unitid><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container id="aspace_c31565fe02fdc4517df14f54ed4b64bb" label="Mixed Materials [39090017918851]" type="box">5</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_1899edc6bade665d2232f7d614334a7f"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>20 years from date of creation.</p></accessrestrict></c><c id="aspace_e03da66e9f0b3a0c1c5ec1421a5a74d0" level="file"><did><unittitle>Mystic River Watershed Association reports and grant applications </unittitle><unitid>UA183-006</unitid><unitdate certainty="approximate" normal="1975/2006" type="inclusive">1975 -- 2006</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container id="aspace_37192ba3f5031069379929374966b4ea" label="Mixed Materials [39090017918869]" type="box">6</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_97cd2b6bb1a869ec40dfc190fe7a02dd"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>20 years from date of creation.</p></accessrestrict></c><c id="aspace_570b5a17eb8e01c989531b7247b909cb" level="file"><did><unittitle>RH Archives Sent 2004 [Rob Hollister subject files]</unittitle><unitid>UA183-007</unitid><unitdate certainty="approximate" normal="2004/2004">2004</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container id="aspace_494100dc59263ae7b886be2ee2c89c76" label="Mixed Materials [39090017918877]" type="box">7</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_758fd3a45067f63f16ccdf4d3e7c3fa6"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>20 years from date of creation.</p></accessrestrict></c><c id="aspace_20271d741c65fe7bc76334942e7c9c27" level="file"><did><unittitle>Files from 2000/2001 Dutho, Omidyar Scholars, Etc.</unittitle><unitid>UA183-008</unitid><unitdate certainty="approximate" normal="2000/2001" type="inclusive">2000 -- 2001</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container id="aspace_f2722d699566407e196c577013a971a8" label="Mixed Materials [39090017918885]" type="box">8</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_f3454f213a9ae6fd0bdb59c30941e509"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>20 years from date of creation.</p></accessrestrict></c><c id="aspace_2acfe0e0ddf1b75ecc32c2e18d52faeb" level="file"><did><unittitle>VHS tapes, DVDs, and Subject Files</unittitle><unitid>UA183-009</unitid><unitdate certainty="approximate" normal="1990/2005" type="inclusive">1990 -- 2005</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container id="aspace_14401e19021e3984f8fdc3de46035e14" label="Mixed Materials [39090017918893]" type="box">9</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_6de2c72f9b3c31dafd62fc2c38c0d9f6"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>20 years from date of creation.</p></accessrestrict></c><c id="aspace_dc87ccf1b7924301021ff27b9e29435f" level="file"><did><unittitle>Rob's (Hollister) Rabb Room Binders</unittitle><unitid>UA183-010</unitid><unitdate certainty="approximate" normal="2005/2007" type="inclusive">2005 -- 2007</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container id="aspace_d9943064a3a82370552f5ea929b62596" label="Mixed Materials [39090017918901]" type="box">10</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_c3206e00ef6d64f010abbd717822569d"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>20 years from date of creation.</p></accessrestrict></c><c id="aspace_eac23fcd44cdb1c5bdd88c0b19f9b833" level="file"><did><unittitle>Rob Hollister Foundation and Grant Files</unittitle><unitid>UA183-011</unitid><unitdate certainty="approximate" normal="1999/2001" type="inclusive">1999 -- 2001</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container id="aspace_95e3ecdefac13352010170e1933fdb48" label="Mixed Materials [39090017918919]" type="box">11</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_d23da16a0dcaeed30bf4e830873f65e6"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>20 years from date of creation.</p></accessrestrict></c><c id="aspace_ab45754f95d81ffca3bc235229cb37d5" level="file"><did><unittitle>Rob's (Hollister) Rabb Closet Files #2 (Development files)</unittitle><unitid>UA183-012</unitid><unitdate certainty="approximate" normal="1999/2005" type="inclusive">1999 -- 2005</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container id="aspace_7069ef4104c3c2bc8a38d5849bde5a42" label="Mixed Materials [39090017918927]" type="box">12</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_691cbd234a34693e4cc9b2ec16d13b55"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>20 years from date of creation.</p></accessrestrict></c></c></dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
