<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd"><eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511"><eadid countrycode="US" url="http://hdl.handle.net/10427/008075">UA223</eadid><filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper>Environmental Studies Program Records<num>UA223</num></titleproper></titlestmt><publicationstmt><publisher>Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University</publisher><p id="logostmt"><extref xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:href="https://dca.tufts.edu/themes/custom/dca_foundation/images/logos/full_with_icon.svg" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple"/></p><address><addressline>35 Professors Row</addressline><addressline>Tisch Library Building</addressline><addressline>Tufts University</addressline><addressline>Medford, Massachusetts 02155</addressline><addressline>archives@tufts.edu</addressline><addressline>URL: <extptr xlink:href="https://dca.tufts.edu/" xlink:show="new" xlink:title="https://dca.tufts.edu/" xlink:type="simple"/></addressline></address></publicationstmt></filedesc><profiledesc><creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on <date>2021-04-10 19:12:07 -0400</date>.</creation></profiledesc></eadheader><archdesc level="collection">
  <did>
    <repository>
      <corpname>Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University</corpname>
    </repository>
    <unittitle>Environmental Studies Program Records</unittitle>
    <origination label="Creator">
      <corpname source="local">Environmental Studies Program</corpname>
    </origination>
    <unitid>UA223</unitid>
    <physdesc altrender="whole">
      <extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">2 Digital Object(s)</extent>
    </physdesc>
    <unitdate normal="1997/1998" type="inclusive">1997--1998</unitdate>
    <abstract id="aspace_eb9d6c0d128d8fb8cd398c492d54d1bd">This collection documents the activities of the Environmental Studies program.</abstract>
    <langmaterial id="aspace_22d40e865fc0205f6a6cda6addcf9c7e">English</langmaterial>
  </did>
  <accessrestrict id="aspace_f9ba44a514a3b08dfe5a00efae32ed44">
    <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
<p>This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.</p>  </accessrestrict>
  <arrangement id="aspace_4ca132ee90f1102d09fbffa660e0acbb">
    <head>Arrangement</head>
<p>This collection is organized into one series: Culpeper proposal.</p>  </arrangement>
  <custodhist id="aspace_366a25c11b768562ad052ef8956ae0ef">
    <head>Custodial History</head>
<p>Material removed from UA220 Women's Studies Program during processing.</p>  </custodhist>
  <processinfo id="aspace_ea18fe2d07d5379f531b9731928d16e8">
    <head>Processing status</head>
<p>This collection was processed by Margaret Peachy, Digital Archivist, in June 2020.</p>  </processinfo>
  <scopecontent id="aspace_bb74972c66ec1bf8043abc0e4e609b77">
    <head>Scope and Contents</head>
<p>This collection documents the activities of the Environmental Studies program and includes course materials; one memorandum; and one grant proposal submitted to the Charles Culpeper Foundation.</p>  </scopecontent>
  <userestrict id="aspace_732df0ee0af305b96d31152f9a793a31">
    <head>Conditions Governing Use</head>
<p>Some material in this collection may be protected by copyright and other rights. Please see "Reproductions and Use" on the Digital Collections and Archives website for more information about reproductions and permission to publish. Copyright to all materials created by Tufts University employees in the course of their work is held by the Trustees of Tufts University.</p>  </userestrict>
  <bioghist id="aspace_3f06f5d5ea9f75440626a072211a0efe">
    <head>Biographical / Historical</head>
<p>The Environmental Studies Program (ENVS) began at Tufts in 1984 when Environmental Studies was approved as a major under the direction of Norton H. Nickerson.  The purpose of the Environmental Studies Program was to promote the study of our natural surroundings as one of the first multidisciplinary environmental programs in the U.S. </p><p>The dual-major in the Environmental Studies Program was initially intended to be in conjunction with one of the following major disciplines: Biology, Chemistry, Civil Engineering, Economics, Geology, Mathematics, Physics, and Political Science. In 1992, the Environmental Studies Program, under the direction of Richard Wetzler, expanded the dual major with the creation of a three track system: the Environmental Science track, the Environment and Technology track, and the Environment and Society track, along with core requirements.   After twenty years, the Environmental Studies Program, under the direction of Colin M. Orians, adopted a new track system consisting of four tracks: the Environmental Science track, the Sustainability, Policy, and Equity track, the Environmental Communications track, and the Self-Designed with Advisor track.  The track system has continued to change to better suit the vision of the Environmental Studies Program. </p><p>The Environmental Studies Program has followed its purpose of promoting the study of the environment, studying designs to help limit the degradation of the environment, and providing social and political resources to preserve and improve the environment by expanding its curriculum. In 2013, the Environmental Studies Program created a minor in Environmental Science and Policy for Engineers.  In 2016, the Environmental Studies Program added a minor in Food Systems and Nutrition that is open to all undergraduate students.  The Environmental Studies Program expanded beyond its curriculum. In 2013, the Environmental Studies Program and the Office of Sustainability introduced the Sustainability House on Latin Way as an option for undergraduate housing.  The Lunch and Learn Seminar Series began in 2015 as a way to bring in speakers from different backgrounds to give presentations on environmental topics. </p>  </bioghist>
  <controlaccess>
    <subject source="local">Curriculum and Instruction -- Academic Departments and Programs</subject>
  </controlaccess>
  <dsc><c id="aspace_3e5c8959cf6dbc1fd453850c15539ff7" level="series"><did><unittitle>Culpeper proposal</unittitle><unitid>UA223.00001</unitid><physdesc altrender="whole"><extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">2 Digital Object(s)</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1997/1998" type="inclusive">1997--1998</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><arrangement id="aspace_8e57ec5d65ab1a1abc9dc3d2c9b785f7"><head>Arrangement</head><p>This series is arranged in two parts: materials that are open for research and materials that are restricted.</p></arrangement><accessrestrict id="aspace_5c6edff0ef16d706468478c41f247e60"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>This series contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_2c056e2bd2a39ff0990a50254c599339"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>This series contains the contents of a 3.5 inch floppy disk labeled "Culpeper Proposal." Files that are open for research include proposal materials and teaching materials produced by Richard Wetzler. Closed materials include lists of students in the Environmental Studies major.</p></scopecontent><c id="aspace_4f33fb9df712f8eca46c1e1102def414" level="item"><did><unittitle>Culpeper proposal</unittitle><unitid>UA223.000004</unitid><physdesc altrender="whole"><extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">1 Digital Object(s)</extent></physdesc><physdesc altrender="whole"><extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">1 Megabytes</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1997/1998" type="inclusive">1997 -- 1998</unitdate></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_3fec7a3963c666be215038e4ede0d78b"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_3fa3d8ce3febf182902a16e39dc78931"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>Files related to a Proposal for the Charles E. Culpeper Foundation and teaching materials created by Richard Wetzler.</p></scopecontent></c><c id="aspace_61b43b9b198234d152adea2b9990f1be" level="item"><did><unittitle>Major lists</unittitle><unitid>UA223.000005</unitid><physdesc altrender="whole"><extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">1 Digital Object(s)</extent></physdesc><physdesc altrender="whole"><extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">274 Kilobytes</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1997/1997">1997</unitdate></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_6240c0945cb9590c838fec4cb1d45d7b"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>75 years from date of creation.</p></accessrestrict><scopecontent id="aspace_2f7bfd5ee2504bf480f1e1cd91ef0f7c"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>Zip file contains seven files. Six files represent major lists that are closed for 75 years - three in their original format and three in preservation format. The last file is unreadable at the time of ingest into the dark archive and can be revisited.</p></scopecontent></c></c></dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
