<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd"><eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511"><eadid countrycode="US" url="http://hdl.handle.net/10427/003613">MS162</eadid><filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper>Charles E. Fay Papers<num>MS162</num></titleproper></titlestmt><publicationstmt><publisher>Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University</publisher><p id="logostmt"><extref xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:href="https://dca.tufts.edu/themes/custom/dca_foundation/images/logos/full_with_icon.svg" xlink:show="embed" xlink:type="simple"/></p><address><addressline>35 Professors Row</addressline><addressline>Tisch Library Building</addressline><addressline>Tufts University</addressline><addressline>Medford, Massachusetts 02155</addressline><addressline>archives@tufts.edu</addressline><addressline>URL: <extptr xlink:href="https://dca.tufts.edu/" xlink:show="new" xlink:title="https://dca.tufts.edu/" xlink:type="simple"/></addressline></address></publicationstmt></filedesc><profiledesc><creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on <date>2021-04-10 19:13:48 -0400</date>.</creation></profiledesc></eadheader><archdesc level="collection">
  <did>
    <repository>
      <corpname>Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University</corpname>
    </repository>
    <unittitle>Charles E. Fay Papers</unittitle>
    <origination label="Creator">
      <persname source="local">Fay, Charles Ernest </persname>
    </origination>
    <unitid>MS162</unitid>
    <physdesc altrender="whole">
      <extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">0.55 Linear Feet</extent>
      <extent altrender="carrier">1 box</extent>
    </physdesc>
    <unitdate normal="1866/1942" type="inclusive">1866 -- 1942</unitdate>
    <langmaterial>
      <language langcode="eng">English</language>
.    </langmaterial>
  </did>
  <accessrestrict id="aspace_d489e03f1cc42fbc4074937b5af6d969">
    <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
<p>This collection is open for research.</p>  </accessrestrict>
  <arrangement id="aspace_6eaef67747e24abbf46d43b79d8070c9">
    <head>Arrangement</head>
<p>This collection is organized into one series.</p>  </arrangement>
  <bioghist id="aspace_1594d04c82395976528f93c943a6be51">
    <head>Biographical / Historical</head>
<p>Charles Ernest Fay (1846-1931) had a long career with Tufts. He attended Tufts as a student from 1865-1868 and served as a professor of modern languages for sixty years (1868-1928), as well as the Secretary of the School of Arts and Sciences (1873-1881) and as the Dean of the Graduate School (1912-1923).</p>

<p>Charles E. Fay was born in Roxbury, Massachusetts on March 10, 1846. He was the son of Cyrus H. Fay, a Universalist clergyman, and Anne Hyne (Minifie) Fay, a native of England. Upon graduating from high school in Providence, Rhode Island, he began his teaching career in Nashua, New Hampshire. He then took a position as the Master of Middle District Grammar School in Bristol, Rhode Island. Fay decided to attend college in 1864, but spent his first year at Tufts as a private student of Heman A. Dearborn learning Latin in order to meet the ancient language requirement for admission. In 1865 he was admitted to Tufts as a regular student and graduated with honors in 1868.</p>

<p>Upon graduation, Charles E. Fay began his teaching career at Tufts as a Walker Special Instructor of Mathematics. In 1869 he accepted a position as an instructor of modern languages on the terms that he could take a year-long leave of absence in Europe to increase his proficiency in the languages he would be teaching.  In Italy, Fay met Mary W. Lincoln, a Boston native, whom he married in 1870. In 1871, Charles E. Fay was promoted to full professor, holding the title of Wade Professor of Modern Languages and teaching undergraduate courses in French, Italian, and German until his retirement in 1928.  He was universally respected and liked by students, faculty, and administrators. Fay also served as the Secretary of the Faculty of the College of Letters between 1873 and 1881, and as the Dean of the Graduate School from 1912 to 1924. Throughout his career he was awarded two honorary degrees from Tufts, a Doctorate of Literature (1900) and a Doctorate of Laws (1928). </p>

<p>Fay was also active in a number of local and national professional organizations. He was co-founder of the Modern Language Association of America, secretary of the Southern New England Association of Colleges, a lifelong member of the American Philological Association, and president of the New England Modern Language Association. Fay was also a member of several local clubs, including the Boston Shakespeare Club, the Boston Browning Society, the Round Table of Boston, and the Massachusetts Forestry Association.</p>

<p>Charles E. Fay was an avid mountaineer and alpinist, a pioneer of the Canadian Rockies where he ascended over 18 mountains between 1895 and 1913. He was a member of the Appalachian Mountain Club, a founder of the American Alpine Club, and an editor of their journal, Alpina Americana. In 1920, Fay was sent to Monaco as an American delegate to the International Congress of Alpine Clubs, where he was knighted by Prince Albert.</p>

<p>Charles E. Fay died on January 25th, 1931 at Massachusetts General Hospital from complications of appendicitis. He was survived by his widow, Mary Fay, and three children, including Margaret Fay (Tufts Class of 1904). A bas-relief depicting Fay was installed in Goddard Chapel on Tufts Campus. The college was also presented with a memorial portrait of Charles E. Fay on Alumni Day in 1946.  </p>  </bioghist>
  <processinfo id="aspace_ba533b0a0fb32ba3a134667324b60cae">
    <head>Processing Information</head>
<p>This collection was processed by MacKenzie Brigham in fall 2009, supervised by Susanne Belovari.  This collection was originally part the Digital Collection and Archives vertical files, collected by Russell Miller and was pulled to create a separate collection due to the size and significance of the material and person.  Archivist provided folder titles in brackets, and rehoused material acid-free folders.  Since folded newsprint and Fay's folded 1866 Latin thesis were disintegrating along the folds, photocopies were made and housed with the originals; Fay's thesis was housed in a separate folder to prevent further damage.  DCA decided to keep newsprint but as these newspapers are available elsewhere, there were not unfolded and stored separately. The collection also contained recent reference requests, which were either discarded or, when including pertinent historical information, were put into the collection documentation folder.</p>  </processinfo>
  <processinfo id="aspace_4f07c37cd4a8a615e00fbf56eb7652f3">
    <head>Processing status</head>
<p>This collection is processed.</p>  </processinfo>
  <scopecontent id="aspace_671b84c9e97136262f79085c3f7ffe37">
    <head>Scope and Contents</head>
<p>This collection includes correspondence, photographs, and articles documenting the life and career of Charles E. Fay. Included are newspaper clippings and articles from 1879 to 1916 that exhibit Fay's interest and relevance in turn-of-the-century mountaineering and alpinism. The collection also includes photographs from 1868 until Fay's retirement in 1928.Significant topics in this collection include Dr. Fay's publications on linguistics; his personal life as a Tufts University student, as well as student life at Tufts in the 1870s; his professional duties as a Tufts University Professor of Modern Languages (1873-1881), Secretary of the School of Arts and Sciences (1873-1881) and Dean of the Graduate School (1912-1923); and his personal interest in mountaineering and alpinism.</p>  </scopecontent>
  <userestrict id="aspace_ed4ade8f0e5b33957727f2d4423b3e40">
    <head>Conditions Governing Use</head>
<p>Some material in this collection may be protected by copyright and other rights. Please see "Reproductions and Use" on the Digital Collections and Archives website for more information about reproductions and permission to publish. No documentation is available regarding the intellectual property rights in this collection.</p>  </userestrict>
  <controlaccess>
    <title source="local">Fay, Charles Ernest</title>
    <subject source="local">Faculty papers</subject>
    <subject source="local">Alumni and alumnae</subject>
    <subject authfilenumber="sh 85087816&#9;   " source="lcsh">Mountaineering -- Research</subject>
    <subject source="local">University history</subject>
    <subject source="lcsh">Tufts University -- History</subject>
  </controlaccess>
  <dsc><c id="aspace_64810aaf6210bea30e9c018f63348cdb" level="series"><did><unittitle>Subject files</unittitle><unitid>MS162.001</unitid><physdesc altrender="whole"><extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">0.5 Linear Feet</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1866/1942" type="inclusive">1866 -- 1942</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial></did><scopecontent id="aspace_b6040679dd3e8fd78ef03630b30538a7"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>This collection is composed of correspondence, photographs and articles documenting the life and career of Charles E. Fay.  Papers of Charles E. Fay include biographical sketches of Fay in manuscript form, as well as biographical newspaper clippings and articles from Tufts publications.  Correspondence includes letters written by Fay to Tufts administrators throughout the course of his career at Tufts (1868-1928), as well as articles written by Fay on the subject of linguistics.  Biographical subject file also contains Fay's mortgage and contract from his home on the intersection of Packard Street and Professor's Row.  His 'Latin Thesis' is a rare example of school work by an early Tufts student, and a few selected notes and class schedules from 1874 document student life at this time.  Mountaineering material include articles written by Fay about his mountain-climbing experiences and his interest in the Canadian Rockies, as well as membership registers and publications of the Appalachian Mountain Club.  Photographs show Fay throughout his Tufts career.</p></scopecontent><arrangement id="aspace_53697748adc3434fd104d5c822b69dc2"><head>Arrangement</head><p>This series is arranged alphabetically.</p></arrangement><accessrestrict id="aspace_6740cbea1f3820b88901ecd0c760f1ad"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict><c id="aspace_b8d40172b05b0cd50f97bea84342a6ab" level="file"><did><unittitle>[Biographical]</unittitle><unitid>MS162.001.001.00001</unitid><unitdate normal="1868/1931" type="inclusive">1868 -- 1931</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container altrender="Letter size document box" id="aspace_1ab78f44469437ebc5b8731ddf3e2d77" label="Mixed Materials [39090015514322]" type="box">1</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_5ecf49867e55da3573892cb353840baf"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict></c><c id="aspace_d536b458c9cc6e43f1eebb925d409bbb" level="file"><did><unittitle>[Biographical]</unittitle><unitid>MS162.001.001.00002</unitid><unitdate normal="1914/1932" type="inclusive">1914 -- 1932</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container altrender="Letter size document box" id="aspace_cc53f36a986526122917125b7a2bfd73" label="Mixed Materials [39090015514322]" type="box">1</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_65c8f5a9c5544b13a600076ee2b89ea0"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict></c><c id="aspace_c86613b2fe6c71ae5476b36370fbf8d3" level="file"><did><unittitle>[Latin Thesis]</unittitle><unitid>MS162.001.001.00003</unitid><unitdate normal="1866/1866" type="inclusive">1866</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container altrender="Letter size document box" id="aspace_b16e8c8245c821fd0fa608d2a9b548ad" label="Mixed Materials [39090015514322]" type="box">1</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_e4e3f2f88b077f8c44c07748ce69a1a2"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict></c><c id="aspace_60f9369f09932b701f4880f7fbe84b48" level="file"><did><unittitle>[Mountaineering Articles]</unittitle><unitid>MS162.001.001.00004</unitid><unitdate normal="1877/1922" type="inclusive">1877 -- 1922</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container altrender="Letter size document box" id="aspace_02efe10b270c2dda72f158f994450c6b" label="Mixed Materials [39090015514322]" type="box">1</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_f7abe090a0dd92b8aee0d29a524d34d5"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict></c><c id="aspace_f2c9c5bcbe2f5ad4f72e693292b432b2" level="file"><did><unittitle>[Photographs]</unittitle><unitid>MS162.001.001.00005</unitid><unitdate normal="1868/1928" type="inclusive">1868 -- 1928</unitdate><langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>.</langmaterial><container altrender="Letter size document box" id="aspace_db5d070cfc90247d734d4311bac22e43" label="Mixed Materials [39090015514322]" type="box">1</container></did><accessrestrict id="aspace_065bead4b97a650e976fff5a040da14f"><head>Conditions Governing Access</head><p>Open for research.</p></accessrestrict></c></c></dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
